with we believed
with we believed
President Zhang, distinguished guests, welcome to today's feast of knowledge
張校長 各位貴賓非常歡迎各位來參加今天的知識饗宴
So today we are very honored to invite President Zhang Guoen, President of National Normal University
那麼今天我們非常榮幸能請到國立示範大學校長張國恩校長
Demonstration universities are leaders in domestic education circles
示範大學是國內教育界的龍頭
So today he will talk about a topic that also belongs to his profession.
那他今天來講一個也是屬於他本行的題目
Research on the Application of Information Technology in Education
就是資訊科技在教育的應用研究
Principal Zhang is a very outstanding scholar in this field
張校長是非常傑出的這方面的學者
He was once a professor and librarian at the National Model University
他曾經得過 他曾經擔任國立示範大學的教授兼圖書館館長
Professor and Vice-Chancellor and then President of Model University since February 2010
教授兼副校長 然後在2010年的2月開始擔任示範大學校長
He's very young. He's 47 years old.
他年紀非常輕 他是47年次的
So I think he is the youngest national university president in the country
所以我認為他是國內最年輕的國立大學校長
But he just reminded me that there is another one, but the scale of the school cannot be compared with the Normal University.
不過他剛提醒我還有一個比不過那個學校規模不能跟師大相比
So he's a very young, promising and highly academically accomplished principal.
那麼他是非常年輕 有為而且學術成就很高的校長
He is a very representative scholar in his field
他在他的領域是一個很代表性的學者
He has won two National Science Council Excellence Awards
他曾經得過國科會兩次傑出獎
a total of six years
總共六年
he too
他也是
Executive Director of Zhizhihui
知測會的常務董事
especially important
尤其重要的是
As far as I know, he is the founder of the Digital Learning Quality Certification Center
我的瞭解他是數位學習品質認證中心的創辦人
centralized builder
集中造集人
Then this center is in my impression
那麼這個中心在我印象中
Certification and Promotion of Digital Learning in Taiwan
對台灣的數位學習的認證跟推動
had a great effect
產生了很大的作用
Professor Zhang and I have a special marriage
張教授跟我有一個特殊的姻緣
Because of a national action plan funded by the National Science Council
因為國科會幫補助的一個國家行計畫
Digital Archives and Digital Learning National Program
叫數位點長與數位學習國家行計畫
Then this year and next year will end
那麼今年明年就要結束了
So this project is ten years old
那麼這個計畫有十年之久
what about this plan
這個計畫呢
It turned out to be two plans
原來是兩個計畫組成
One is the national travel plan for digital point leaders
一個是數位點長國家行計畫
One is the National Roadmap for Digital Learning
一個是數位學習國家行計畫
National Travel Plan for Digital Point Leaders
數位點長國家行計畫
In my impression
在我印象中
at the very beginning
剛開始的時候
Should be the first in the world
應該是全世界第一個
with the power of the country
以國家的力量
The Power of a National Action Plan
以國家行計畫的力量
to drive digit length
來推動數位點長
then digital learning was established later
那麼數位學習稍晚以後成立
Probably the first in the world
應該也是全世界第一個
I'm not sure about this part
這個部分我比較不清楚
Directly the first of its kind to promote digital learning with a national program
直接第一個以國家型計畫來推動數位學習的這個
The two programs were later merged
這兩個計畫後來合併
then it's a very special project
那麼是一個很有特色的計畫
More than ten years ago, the logarithmic point was long
在十幾年前人們對數位點長
Including me can be said to have no idea
包括我在內可謂毫無概念
I don't know what is the digit length
不知道什麼叫數位點長
After ten years I think many people
經過十年之後我想很多人
At least you've heard the term
至少都聽過這個名詞
even know how
甚至知道怎麼做
and it's easy to do
而且很簡單就會做
Nobody heard of digital learning even a decade ago
在十幾年前也沒有人聽過數位學習
At least I'm not familiar with this myself
至少我自己也不熟悉這個
But now Taiwan's top 1,000 companies
可是現在台灣的一千大企業
Basically almost all have been more or less
基本上幾乎都已經或多或少
Using digital learning to train employees
用到數位學習來做員工的訓練
So I think the development of these two fields
所以我想這兩個領域的發展
It's very special in our country
在我們國家是很特別
Principal Zhang Guoen is a leader in digital learning
而張國恩校長就是數位學習這方面的領導人
He just said what I just introduced
他剛剛所我剛剛所介紹
Digital Learning Quality Certification Center
數位學習品質認證中心
He is the founder and general convener
他是創辦人跟總召集人
And he also serves as a digital point chief
而且他還擔任數位點長
Co-host with Digital Learning National Initiative
跟數位學習國家計畫的共同主持人
I am the host
我是主持人
So the co-hosts of the digit-long segment
那麼在數位點長的部分的共同主持人
Center Adult Principal
中心大人校長
He used to be the director of the Information Institute, Zhongyan Information Institute
他原來是資訊所 中研資訊所所長
He is the person in charge of the digital learning side.
那數位學習那邊的負責人就是他
So today we are very honored
所以今天我們非常榮幸
Can invite such an important scholar
能請到這個這麼重要的一位學者
Let's talk about a subject he's doing well
來談他當行出色的一個題目
Research on the Application of Information Technology in Education
就是資訊科技在教育的應用研究
We welcome Mr. Zheng with warm applause
我們熱烈掌聲歡迎鄭老師
Thanks
謝謝
We thank Mr. Wang Huyan
我們謝謝王滬燕長
In addition, there are many old seniors of mine here.
另外在座有很多我的老學長
and our school teachers
還有我們學校的老師
and classmates
還有同學
In addition, representatives from various
另外有各方面的代表
then i want to be very happy
那我想非常高興
And it's a great honor to be here
而且也非常榮幸能夠來這邊
Share our information technology with you
跟各位分享我們資訊科技
Applications and research in education as part of
在教育上的應用跟研究的一個部分
Then I think this field has developed to the present
那我想這個領域發展到現在
In fact, it's been almost 20 years
事實上已經有將近20年的歷史了
from the earliest very simple
那從最早期的一種很簡單的
One is used in the classroom
一個在教室裡面應用
We call it the Association for Integrating Education
我們把它稱為資訊融入教協
Until now, apart from the integration of information into blood
一直到現在除了資訊融入交血以外
but also promote to industrial application
還要推動到產業應用
Especially the computer has changed a lot
尤其電腦的變化非常大
Now there are camp technology and mobile technology
現在有營端科技 有行動載技
So its platform is getting more and more complex
所以它的平台又越來越複雜
then we all know the theory of trading
那我們都知道交易的理論
It's a hundred years old It's a hundred years old
已經有百年的歷史 已經有百年的歷史
But this century-old history usually takes place in
但是這個百年的歷史通常發生在
Classroom Inside the actual classroom
教室 實際的教室裡面
a result obtained
所得到的一個結果
But now there is an information platform
可是現在有資訊平台
The information platform is very complicated
那資訊這個平台又非常複雜
A platform with a marketing platform A platform with mobile technology
有營端的平台 有行動載技的平台
Internet-based platform
有網路的平台
Of course there are platforms for personalized learning
那當然個人化學習的平台都有
So under such a platform
所以在這樣的平台底下
we may have to rethink
我們可能要重新思考
Think about how to develop
思考怎麼來發展
A Variation in Trading Theory
在交易理論的一個變化
how to apply
怎麼來應用
Put information technology on top of our entire school
把資訊科技擺在我們整個交學上面
There are also students' self-learning
還有學生的自我學習上面
But because of such Yangu
可是因為有這樣的顏固
It does raise a lot of questions
的確引申非常多的問題
what's the problem
怎麼問題呢
Children often forget themselves as long as they are in front of the computer
小孩子只要在電腦面前常常忘記自己了
so there will be a phenomenon of fame
所以會有一種成名的現象
The so-called poisoning happened.
就所謂很像那個中毒的那種情況產生
It's very easy to develop a warm habit
那非常容易養成溫馨的一種習慣
If Xin Xin gets used to it, there will be a big problem
溫馨如果變習慣的話問題就很大
big problem
問題就很大
So he does have a lot of hangovers
所以他的確有很多後遺症
that under such aftermath
那在這樣的後遺症底下
how do we apply it
我們怎麼把它應用進來
At present, Taiwan is integrating information into classroom teaching.
那目前台灣在資訊融入到課堂教學裡面
I think there should be a history of 15 years
我想應該有15年的一個歷史
Now most of the teachers have the means to use computers to help his teaching
現在大部分的老師都有辦法用電腦來幫助他的教學
The student also has the means to use the computer to aid his own learning
那學生也有辦法用電腦來幫助他自己的學習
So where is the problem now?
那現在問題是在哪裡呢
Today's technology changes too much
現在的科技變化太多
Because there are many sequelae
因為有很多後遺症
So how do we import more bone-setting places
所以我們怎麼導入比較正骨的地方
Then let this bone-setting place make a greater contribution to education
然後讓這個正骨的地方可以對教育有更大的一個貢獻
I will go to the mainland for a while
一陣子我到大陸
Central China Normal University
那到華中師大
That's when I knew they had a big, big plan.
那我才知道他們有一個很大很大的計畫
Taiwan probably can't compare
我們台灣大概不能比的
It is also a plan to promote information and agriculture into teaching
也是要推動資訊、農入教學的計畫
Related to Elanin
跟Elanin有關
His promotion is an astronomical figure
他的推動經會是一個天文數字
300 billion RMB
三千億人民幣
is very scary
是非常可怕
Therefore, it means that the production value of this supernatural power is also very large.
所以表示這個靈異的產值也是很大
but we also know
但是我們也知道
They hardly know how to push
他們幾乎不知道怎麼推動
He's a lot like what we were like twenty years ago
他很像我們大概二十年前的那種樣子
When information first arrives in education
資訊第一次到教育來的時候
don't know how to push
不知道怎麼去推動
So from an industry point of view
所以從以產業界的角度而言
Our business opportunity is great
我們的商機是很大
we can make their money
我們可以賺他們的錢
but we can teach him what was ten years ago
但是我們可以教他十年前的東西
After he had reached ten years ago
等他十年前已經達到之後
We have progressed for ten years
我們就進步十年了
So use an angle like this
所以用這樣的一個角度
In addition to this, there is actually another very important
那除了這個以外其實還有一個非常重要
There may be a big change recently
最近可能會有很大的一個改變
Twelve Years International
十二年國際
In fact, in the past 12 years, I think about Taiwan's future development
其實十二年國家我想對台灣未來的一個發展
If we look at it from a long-term perspective
如果我們以長年的角度來看的話
It can indeed change the entire education pattern
它的確是可以改變整個教育形態
at least three years
起碼有三年的時間
It used to be six years, now it's three years more
以前是六年 現在多了三年
Therefore, there are nine years in which normal news can be obtained.
所以有九年的時間裡面可以正常消息
We know that it should be under the joint examination system
我們知道應該在聯考制度底下
So our students' academic achievement
所以我們學生的學習成就
Academic achievement of our students High academic achievement
我們學生的學習成就 學習成就高的
It does not mean that its future competitiveness is high
並不表示它未來的競爭力是高的
Especially in the era of Internet, computerization and technology
尤其在網路時代 電腦化 科技時代底下
you have so much ability we must develop
你有太多能力我們必須培養
For example, we often say that we want to promote night reading
譬如說我們常常說我們要推動夜讀
children need to read more night
小孩子要多夜讀
But the ranking of our night reading
可是我們的夜讀的排名
Ranking is not high in the world
在全球的排名就是不高
I'm not tall, I remember like
我就不高 我記得好像是
is better than that one
是比那個一個
One that is lower in Macau
一個那個澳門還低
Macau is a gambling country
澳門是一個賭博的國家
We come in for night reading part is lower than theirs
我們進來夜讀的部分比他們還低
How could such a problem be caused?
怎麼會造成這樣的一個問題呢
Because our education stage
因為我們的教育階段裡面
from primary school
從小學開始
First grade through high school
一年級一直到高中階段
We never teach students to find jobs
我們從來沒有教學生找業讀
We also never teach students
我們也從來沒有教學生
Get it from reading
從業讀裡面去得到
get very interesting
得到非常有趣的事項
we just let him read
我們只是讓他讀
But you can see
可是各位可以看得出來
when do we teach young children
我們什麼時候教小孩子
Organize knowledge from professional reading
從業讀裡面去整理知識
Find out the key points in the professional reading
從業讀裡面去找出重點
These organize knowledge and find out the key points
這些整理知識跟找出重點
It is often made by our Pingliang
常常都是我們的平良本做出來的
we are not now
我們不是現在
Middle school has to take the entrance exam for high school and high school has to take the exam for university
國中要考高中高中要考大學
There are many booksellers who have created many Pingliang editions.
都有很多書商建了很多平良本
how to organize this
那怎麼去整理這個
Then I said why this sequelae
那我說為什麼這個後遺症會
getting bigger
越來越大呢
There are too many things to read in the Internet age
網路時代底下太多業讀的東西
is on the Internet
是在網路上面
But even this basic quality
可是我們連這個基本的素養
did not build
都沒有去建立的話
Information provided by the Internet age
網路時代所提供的資訊
Instead, many students
反而對很多學生
students are a burden
學生是一個負擔
is a burden
是一個負擔
So there is a side effect like too many
所以有造成類似太多的這樣的一個後遺症
So I said why the influence of the country will be so great in 12 years
所以我說12年國家為什麼影響會那麼大的
because we at least
因為我們起碼
If our policy is done well
如果我們政策做得很好的話
all our parents
我們所有的家長
If you brighten his thoughts and eyes
把他的想法 把他的眼光晃明一點的話
maybe we can cultivate
也許我們可以培養
What we call in educational terms
我們所謂的在教育名詞裡面
Make it Metascale
把它成為Metascale
Metagability
Metagability
so-called metacapabilities
所謂的後設能力
What is meta-capability
什麼叫後設能力
That is to say, I can activate the ability of knowledge
就是說我可以啟用知識的能力
I can activate the ability in my brain knowledge
我可以啟用我腦筋知識裡面的能力
For example, your communication skills
譬如說你的溝通能力
your ability to read
你的閱讀的能力
your inquiry skills
你的探究能力
right
對不對
wait for these abilities
等等這些能力
Opportunities that can be cultivated in the future
以後可以被培養出來的機會
should be more
應該會比較多一點
Of course there is a very important premise
當然有一個非常重要的前提
we must make good use of
我們必須好好利用
extra three years
多出來的三年
Make an overall plan for the whole course
把整個課程做一個整體的規劃
I hope that within nine years
希望在利用九年的時間裡面
cultivate these abilities
把這些能力培養出來
Absolutely better than you to cultivate Guoying's learning achievements in natural mathematics
絕對比你培養國英自然數學的學習成就
This manpower is more important
這個人力還要重要
I think this is our big government
我想這個是我們大有的政府
if you can see this
如果可以看到這一點
maybe the twelve kingdoms
也許十二連國教
It is really important for the future development of Taiwan
真的是對台灣未來發展
is a very important opportunity
是一個很重要的一個機會
That's because people today may come from many different places
那因為今天的各位可能來自很多不同的地方
so i assume
所以我就假定
Try to use more common
盡量用比較通俗一點的
In a relatively unprofessional way
用比較沒有專業素養的方式
let's talk about this topic
來談這一個題目
then if there is any question
那如果等一下有任何一個問題
we can discuss
我們可以一起來討論
let me share
我一起來分享
that information is in the educational app itself
那資訊在教育應用本身
There are several tasks and goals
有幾個任務跟目標
Finally, we hope to continue to do
最後我們希望能夠繼續持續的來做
also hope to be able to complete
也希望能夠完成
First
第一個
The first of our learning journey
第一個我們的學習歷程
throughout the learning process
在整個學習歷程的過程裡面
How we use information technology
我們如何利用資訊科技
to help humans learn about human development
來幫助人類學習人力的發展
thank you all
謝謝大家
In fact everyone must have a progress in his learning process
事實上每一個人一定都有他學習過程的一個進展
Then in this learning process
那在這學習過程裡面
For example, if you study
譬如說你業讀
Is there any part in this course of study
在這業讀的過程裡面有沒有哪個部分
We can help through information technology
我們可以透過資訊科技來幫忙
come to help you and can develop some of your academic and reading skills
來幫你而且能夠培養一些你業讀方面的能力
Now an obvious example is ebooks
現在一個很明顯的例子就是電子書
I think everyone knows about e-books
我想電子書大家都很清楚
Whether it is the iPad or our domestic manufacturers
不管是 iPad 也好或者我們國內的廠商
Epad is also good
Epad 也好
The era of e-books has really come
這個電子書的時代真的是已經來了
but where is the problem now
但現在問題在哪裡呢
We now have an e-book for everyone
我們現在電子書每一個人所一本
But can he let us do in-depth homework reading?
但是他可以讓我們做深入業讀嗎
And the way we're designing e-books now
而且我們現在電子書所設計的方式
All are using the Skin reading method
全部都是用 Skin reading 的方法
What is the so-called skin reading
所謂 Skin reading 是讀什麼
general practice book
一般的修行書
He can't help you draw the key points for the first e-book, right?
第一個電子書他也不能幫你畫重點啊對不對
Then you can't write down your thoughts.
那也不能夠你把心得寫進去啊
Like many of our books there are
像我們很多書裡面還有
Then there is a little activity, let you use your brain
那有一個小活動啊,讓你動動腦啊
it has none in it
它裡面都沒有
So in a stage of development like this
所以那這樣子的一個發展的一個階段裡面
Will there be any sequelae on the liquid poison?
會不會在液毒上面有沒有後遺症
But whether this road will go, it will definitely go to Asia
但是這一條路會不會走,一定會往亞走
but this way
可是這樣走
is there a good way
有沒有一個好的方法
channel it into the most important development of our learning human
把它引導到我們學習人力最重要的發展
If you are watching when you were young, watch Jin Yong when you were young
如果你是看小時候,看金庸小時候
maybe it doesn't matter
也許這不重要
it doesn't matter
對這個不重要
But if you read ordinary textbooks
可是如果你是看一般的教科書
Read math, read English, read nature, etc.
看數學,看英文,看自然等等
Let you know how to let you in the whole liquid poisoning process
讓你如何讓在整個液毒的過程裡面
Emphasis on learning workforce development
強調學習人力的發展
So in order to achieve this one
所以為了達到這一個的話
That's obvious from the specifications of our e-book
那很明顯的我們的電子書的規格
to modify
要做修改
That is, it must increase some
也就是它必須要增加一些
The functions related to the study of liquid poison put it in
跟液毒學習有關的功能把它擺進來
Well, there are already many groups doing this
那這個目前已經有很多團體在做
you are working on this one
你在研究這一個
Is it possible to come up with the specifications of a good e-book
是不是可以提出好的電子書的規格
Then on the students' learning
然後對學生的學習上面
it is helpful
它是有幫助的
This is a part worth studying
這個都是值得研究的一個部分
Then in addition now
那另外現在在
In a competitive environment in the 21st century
在二十一世紀的一個競爭力裡面
Because a recent statistic
因為最近有統計一個
in the twenty-first century
在二十一世紀底下
What kind of manpower will affect future competition
有哪一些人力是會影響未來的競爭
you personally will have an impact
就你個人會有一個影響
One of the most important is cooperative learning
其中有一個很重要的是合作學習
a cooperative learning
一個合作學習
this used to be possible
這個以前可能
We in Taiwan rarely pay attention to this
我們台灣很少重視這個
We value personalization
我們重視是個人化形式
Is there any way we can cooperate with others
我們有沒有辦法跟別人合作
Collaborate to solve common problems
合作之後來解決共同的問題
You may need this one to enter the society
你進入社會可能就需要這一個
The ability to cooperate
那這個合作的能力
How to train the ability to cooperate
合作的能力本身怎麼培訓
In the Internet age, it could have helped acting skills
那網路時代本來就可以幫忙演技
in a kaohsiung
在一個高雄
one in japan, one in america, one in taipei
一個在日本,一個在美國,一個在台北
those four
那這四個
How can one work together to solve some problems through the Internet?
一個怎麼合在一起透過網路來共同解決一些問題
Networked Collaborative Learning Capabilities
網路化的一個合作協習的能力
Or the ability to cooperate and solve problems together
或者合作的一種共同解決問題的這個能力
how to build it
那怎麼把它建立起來
So how can we help it in this process
所以在這個過程裡面我們如何來幫助它
This is all in the whole training process
這個都是整個協習歷程裡面
A part of what we hope to be able to achieve
我們希望能夠達到的一個部分
so this is the first
所以這個是第一個
Second, we hope to use the digitized eye of a fellow student
第二個我們希望用數位化的一個協習之眼
To enrich the experience of ability learning
來豐富能力學習的經驗
and learning methods to improve it
以及改善它的學習方法
this is very interesting
這個非常有趣的
once there was a teacher
有一次有一個老師
a primary school teacher
一個國小老師
Then he wants students to find information through the Internet
然後他要希望學生透過網路找資料
and then make a report
然後做一份報告出來
Then I remember his first topic
那我記得他的第一個題目
He wants elementary school students to organize a
他是要小學生透過網路去整理一個
Life of a Butterfly
叫蝴蝶的一生
Then I hope that after the students sort it out
那希望學生把它整理出來之後
then find a report
然後找一個報告
After the result report came out, the teacher was very sad
結果報告講出來之後那個老師就很傷心
Because everyone's homework is similar
因為大家的作業都差不多
Why? Because all use copy passed
為什麼?因為全部都用 copy passed
All with copy passed and no bets
全部都用 copy passed 也沒有賭
students did not gamble
學生也沒有賭
So later he laughed at himself and said
所以後來他就自嘲他說
I was going to let them know that butterflies
本來我要讓他們知道蝴蝶
Turns out it only taught them the human power of the computer
結果只教他們電腦的人力
called copy passed
叫做 copy passed
Nothing else was taught
其他都沒有教到
So Taiwanese teachers are also good.
所以台灣老師也是不錯啦
he will wake up
他都會還醒
He'll think that's wrong
他會想說那這樣不對
this will be problematic
這個會有問題
He later came up with another topic
他後來就出了另外一個題目
like the insect doctor
譬如說昆蟲的醫生
But does he want students to read?
但是他要學生要讀東西嘛
So you're going to teach the insect doctor when the report comes out
所以說你要教昆蟲醫生的報告出來的時候
must focus
一定要畫重點
You have to draw key points to be able to teach
你要畫重點才能夠教出來
As a result, when he got it back, he was very sad again.
結果一收回來之後他又很傷心
Why are you sad?
為什麼很傷心呢?
Because everyone wrote another trick called underline
因為大家又寫了一招叫做 underline
called underline, it will do nothing
叫 underline 那什麼都不會
that will do nothing
那什麼都不會
So you see that computer tools do have a lot of sequelae
那所以你看電腦工具的確有很多後遺症嘛
Then later he thought
然後後來他就想
he doesn't do that much
他這樣也不多
I still can't read anything like this.
這樣寫是還是讀不到東西啊
Originally identified as Baidu Film
本來認定百度影
Learning by doing should be for students to learn by doing
做中學應該是學生來做中學
The result is that the teacher does the middle school by himself
結果都是老師自己做中學
Because he wants to distinguish the difference in nutritional work
因為他要分別養分作業的差別
And it's hard to separate
而且要分別也很困難
Because everyone is similar
因為大家都差不多
So he thought it was wrong
所以他又想那不對
he wants to change the method
他要換一個方法
he said that's good
他說那這樣好
Don't use that word for this
這個你們不要用那個Word
You just use Powerpoint
你們就用Powerpoint
don't write too much
不要寫太多
All in Powerpoint
全部用Powerpoint就好
And he also stipulated that Powerpoint can only be five pages
而且他還規定Powerpoint只能夠五頁
right
對不對
and the focus of each page
而且每一頁的重點
his title
他的標題
set the title
都把標題訂出來
Each bar below that has its own phone
那底下的每一個條有寫成自己的電
In fact, this is a change of concept
其實這個就是一個觀念的改變
that is
就是說
In transaction theory there is a
在交易理論裡面有一個叫做
phonetic writing
音價式的寫行
construction theory
建構理論
Constructive theory he has an emphasis on
建構理論他有一個強調說
all knowledge
所有知識
build by yourself
由自己來建構
what you want
你想要的疾問
self-construction
可是在結真自我建構
must give him a scaffold
一定要給他鷹架
This is like we cover the yellow fish
這個就如同我們蓋黃之魚
give him the scaffold first
要先給他鷹架
After he wrote Ye Duo
等他寫了夜多之後
The scaffolding needs to be removed slowly
鷹架要慢慢把它撤除
So his homework is done with the concept of scaffolding
所以他這個作業就以鷹架的觀念來做
That is to say he brought up a lot of headlines
就是說他提了很多標題
The title is just to tell the students
標題只是要告訴學生
you follow the direction of this title
你按照這個標題的方向
go find your material class
去找你的材料類
This is a bit of belief
這個就有點在信念什麼
human beings who believe in knowledge
信念知識整理的人類
or this
或是這個
As for Powerpoint, teachers don’t have to use it
就Powerpoint不一定要老師用
Students can also use
學生也可以用
Students organize knowledge through Powerpoint
學生透過Powerpoint來整理知識
Where are the resources?
資源在哪裡呢
on the web
在網路上面
but we must also admit
但是我們也必須承認
Too much information on the internet is wrong
網路有太多資訊是錯誤的
right
對不對
and the most wrong
而且錯誤的最
I want to learn the scariest of the above
我想學習上面最可怕的
will cause a lot of misconceptions
就會造成很多迷思概念
What is the concept of myth
什麼叫做迷思概念呢
It's just a false notion that you think you're right
就是你自以為對的錯誤觀念
essentially it's wrong
本質上它是錯的
but you think you're right
但是你是自以為對的
However, if myths and concepts are not rooted in childhood,
可是迷思概念如果從小沒有根正的話
Sometimes growing up is hard
長大有時候都很難根正
There is indeed such a lot of myths on the Internet
網路上的確有這種充滿非常多的迷思概念
if you don't teach your students
如果你不去教學生的話
It is very likely that students will step into the trap of knowledge
那很有可能學生就會踏入知識上的陷阱
That myth must be rectified.
那迷思概念一定要去把它矯正回來
if not corrected back
如果不矯正回來
big problem
問題就很大了
You can do experiments when you go back.
各位回去可以做實驗看看
We have been taught since childhood that
我們從小都被人家灌輸說
what will happen to finger ye liang
手指葉亮會怎麼樣
ears will fall off, right?
耳朵會掉是吧
right
對不對
is this right or wrong
這個是對還是錯
wrong right wrong
錯對不對
Wait a minute and go back up to see if you dare to point
你等一下往上回去看看看你敢不敢指
Many people really dare not point out
很多人真的不敢指
we have done
我們有做過事
Not only dare not point it out, but some point it out reluctantly
不但不敢指就算了有的很勉強的指出來之後
You will solve the strange ears
你都會解了耳朵怪怪
That myth concept is very complicated and difficult to reverse
那個迷思概念是很複雜很難扭轉
So the sooner you get it all out
所以越早把它整段出來
the reverse is better
扭轉過來是越好
It's smart to have a teacher
那有一個老師就很聰明
he
他
he knows us
他明明知道我們
There are a lot of mistakes on the Internet.
網路上裡面有很多是錯的啊
So he can't let Xiesheng look at it casually
所以他不能夠讓協生隨便去看
He just had a homework
他就出了一個作業
that homework is very simple
那作業就很簡單
So once one direction is changed, the whole will be changed
所以一個方向一改之後整個都改
he has a website
他都某一個網站
There are many mistakes in it, and he will tell you
裡面也很多錯 他就告訴你
There are many mistakes in it
裡面也很多錯
But you guys go online and find out what's wrong
但是你們上網把錯找出來
do you know what i mean
你懂我意思嗎
this is one
這個就是一種
Use the words of the Internet to achieve the purpose of cooperation
利用網路之言達到協行的目的
This is a very simple method
這個很簡單的一個作法
So like our digits are long
所以像我們數位點長
Actually there is an important part
其實有一個很重要的部分
Taiwan has many precious things
台灣有非常多很珍貴的東西
We want to do something recently
我們最近想要做一件事情
Of course it has its difficulty
當然有它的困難度啦
For example, because
譬如說我因為
There's a lot of trouble being the principal at Shida University
在施大當校長有一個很麻煩
the most painful thing for me
對我最痛苦的事情
Every time I go to the art exhibition
每次我都要去看畫展
I really can't see some art exhibitions
那看畫展我有的真的看不到
There are some abstractions that I can't see either
有一些抽象我也看不到
don't know how to appreciate
不知道怎麼欣賞
so i was thinking
所以我就在想
if there is someone next to you
如果旁邊有一個人
I have someone to accompany me to see
有一個人陪著我去看
Then they are explaining this painting to me
然後都在跟我解釋這個畫
how nice he is
怎麼欣賞的話他多好
So I sometimes go to the boss of the art department
所以我有時候會找美術系的老闆
teacher go together
老師一起去
And every time they tell me
然後他們每次告訴我說
Just let you read the book by yourself
讓你自己去看書就好了啊
oh
哦
because
因為
because there are many abstractions
因為有很多抽象化
oh
哦
But it's hard to explain
但還難解釋啊
Maybe my math literacy is too low
大概我的美數素養太低了
He didn't bother to explain to me
他還懶得跟我解釋
So I then thought of a question
所以我後來就想到一個問題
Is it possible for me?
那我有沒有可能哦
is it possible
有沒有可能就
I took an iPad
我拿了一個 iPad
He has a camera or an Epad camera
他有相機或者Epad的相機
Then let's take a picture of this picture
然後我們把這張畫照一下
After taking a picture, he will naturally
那照一下之後他自然
Someone who will automatically have a commentary will run out
自動會有解說的人就跑出來
then help me explain
然後幫我做解說
can it be done
能不能做到這樣做
sure
可以啊
Now this technology is called Augmented Reality.
現在這個技術叫做擴增實境啊
We are working on an agreement now
我們現在一個協議就在做啦
right
對不對
like this
類似這樣
Music is the same
音樂也是一樣啊
we listen to music every time
我們每次都要聽音樂
right
對不對
like this week
像這個禮拜
me a week
我一個禮拜
I'm going to be forced to listen to music
我都要被強迫聽一下音樂
Then every time you have to go to the first position
然後每次都要排到第一個位置
I say the first position
我說第一個位置
and put me in the fifth position
然後給我排到第五個位置
so i saw you later and said
所以我後來看了你說
not the first position
不要第一個位置
What move do we have? Fifth position
我們有什麼動作呢?第五個位置
that's the same
那也是一樣
you always have to understand
你總是要聽得懂
So we just want to say
所以我們就想說
Is there any technology to help us look at the music industry?
那有沒有科技來幫助我們看音業
I don't use the listening industry, but the watching industry
我不要用聽音業,用看音業
What do I use to take a picture and take a picture of it
我用什麼一照,照把它譜照下來
or after taking a picture
或什麼照下來之後
it naturally explains to me
它就自然而然幫我解說
I explain a whole change this whole night
我解說這個整個夜期的一個整個變化
That's why I say technology can achieve this
所以我說科技都可以達到這樣
it is a secondary attack
它是一個輔助攻擊
Then in our digital content
那我們數位內容裡面
There are actually a lot of works of art in the collection
典藏的東西其實有非常多的藝術品
that's a lot of interesting stuff
那非常多有趣的東西
that interesting thing
那這個有趣的東西
Can it become a learning eye?
能不能變成一個學習之眼
How can this place be a family?
那這個地方怎麼做一個家子
Let something die, a treasured thing
讓死的東西,一個典藏的東西
In the end, it becomes a living teaching material
最後變成是一個活的教學的一個材料
I think it's worth dealing with
我想這個都值得我們去處理的
In addition, there is another
另外,另外還有一個是
whole learning technology
整個學習科技
Resources that can make our digital learning
可以讓我們的數位學習的資源
Can do sustainable use and development
可以做永續的使用跟發展
I still can't think of how to use it
現在還想不到怎麼用的話
after that you can't imagine
那以後你想不到
for example
譬如說
in education technology
在在在教育科技裡面
The first was the personal computer
最早的就是個人電腦
Then slowly developed into the Internet age
然後慢慢發展到網路時代
Then the Internet age put
然後網路時代就把
place of acting
演的地方
Various people put it together
各種不同的人就把它站合起來
right
對不對
and then progress to mobile vehicles
然後再發展到行動載具
Now Yingduan Technology
現在營端科技
and then a variety of
然後各種的一種
The technology of information application is getting more and more advanced
資訊應用的技術越來越先進
Then the e-book came again
然後電子書又來了
Then the change function of the function of the camera is
然後相機的功能的變更功能又
getting better and better
又越來越好
so sometimes say
所以有有時候說
Although our resources
雖然我們所存的資源
Now we don't know how to use
現在我們不知道怎麼用
But maybe after a certain stage of technological development
但是可能科技的發展到某一個階段之後
Its use comes naturally
它的用途就自然而然就跑出來
i just ran out
我就跑出來
But do you want a Suviva?
但是要不要蘇威瓦
Because Suviva can make us finer
因為蘇威瓦可以讓我們更詠細的
save that side
保存在那一邊
Then there will be a chance to use
那以後就有機會來來使用
Then there is another one
那另外還有一個是
Implementation of information education
資訊教育的實施
Hope to improve the former
希望能夠提升前名的
digital literacy
數位的素養
Of course now what we call
當然現在我們所謂的
Digital literacy does not mean how high your credit standing is
數位素養不是說你的資信能力有多高
right
對不對
You are not all...
你不是所有資...
not all citizens
不是讓所有的國民
write credit science
都去寫資信科學
no
不是
Instead, use existing credit tools
而是利用現有的資信工具
how to solve his problem
如何來解決他的問題
solve his life problems
解決他生活上的問題
solve his learning problems
解決他學習上的問題
This becomes increasingly important
這個就變得越來越重要的一個
One training for one ability
一個能力的一個培訓
It's already booked
那目前有訂出來啦
of course there is an audience
當然有觀眾
There are about six core competencies in digital literacy
數位素養大概有六大核心能力
Six core competencies
六大核心能力
Each core competency has one
那每一個核心能力有一個
Various types of indicators
各種不同類的指標
then we wish to say
那我們希望說
Future Credit Courses
以後的資信的課程
From elementary school to university
從國小一直到大學
Of course, this is excluding the sacrifice of undergraduate credit department
當然這邊是排除資信本科系的犧牲
Is an ordinary student
是一般的學生
you are a law student
你是法律系的學生
You are a student of the Chinese Department
你是國文系的學生
Then what kind of credit quality should you keep in mind?
那你應該要記備什麼樣的資信的素養
this is
這個是
is more and more important
是越來越重要
at least the first
起碼第一個
We saw
我們看到
After you take it, after you touch it
拿來之後 你摸一摸之後
You can use at least 50% or 60% of the functions
你起碼百分之五六十的功能你就會用
Now children and students
現在小孩子跟學生
Almost everything can be solved like this
幾乎都可以這樣解決
They also rarely read the manual
他們也很少看那個手冊
rarely read that manual
很少看那個手冊
like you hold a cell phone
像你拿一個手機
For the students, I don't think they will read the manual
給學生的話 我想他們都不會看手冊
He takes it, touches it, hits it
他拿來就摸一摸 打一把就
That's the way we are, but we can't see it.
那反而我們這一種 反而沒辦法看
And now we don't know what
而且現在我們不知道什麼樣
Our Dean Wang Hu wrote the article
我們王沪院長寫文寫的
Our current Guowen ability seems to be relatively poor
我們現在果文的能力好像比較差
So that manual
所以那個手冊
I don't know that the manual is influenced by politicians
那個手冊不知道是政治人物影響
because of jump thinking
因為跳躍式的思考
So what was written in the manual is really jumpy enough.
所以那個手冊寫的實在是有夠跳躍
you really don't know what he's writing
你真的不知道他在寫什麼
right but it's weird
對不對 可是很奇怪
Why can't young people understand
年輕人怎麼不看得懂
we don't understand
我們都看不太懂
It may be that the result of the training is not the same
可能是受訓的一個結果不太一樣
That's rare. Now there are few such manuals.
那很少 現在已經很少有這種manual
Almost you go online, you have to go online if you want to read the manual
幾乎你上網 你要看manual都要上網
The basic application ability will become more and more clear
基本的應用能力會越來越清楚
Now what is our biggest concern for the next generation, you know?
那現在下一代我們最擔心的是什麼你知道
cyber crime
網路犯罪
This is cybercrime is a serious problem
這個是網路犯罪是一個很嚴重的問題
it's sometimes a temptation
這有時候是一種誘惑
Well, we have come across a few cases
那我們曾經有碰過幾個案例
It may be that our own education has not been done well.
可能是我們自己教育也沒有做好
Then let the children really face legal problems
然後讓小孩子真的是面臨到法律的問題
especially at what stage
尤其在什麼階段
After high school
高中考大學之後
And it just so happened that these students just retired
而且剛剛好這些學生剛好退徵
push into the university
推徵到大學裡面
he already has school practice
他已經有學校練了
But before entering the university formally, there may be
可是到正式進入大學以前可能有
three to four months or even half a year
三四個月的時間甚至半年的時間
Because of rejection, isn't he?
因為推徵入學嘛他不是
He didn't just pass the exam, right?
他不是直考進去的嘛對不對
so for a long time
所以有一段很長的時間
But everyone ignores a lot
可是大家都忽略掉很多
So if there are any parents here
所以各位在座如果有家長
Children are very careful just at this stage
小孩子剛好在這個階段就很小心
They just turned eighteen
他們剛剛好百十八歲
Many children do not know
很多小孩子自己都不知道
in our law
在我們的法例裡面
18 is an adult
滿18歲就是成年了
So they were bored for a while
所以他們那一段時間又很無聊
often on the site
常常上網站
then do something you shouldn't do
然後做一些不該做的事情
they may find it interesting
他們可能覺得有趣
these suspects find it funny
這些嫌疑人覺得很有趣
He also thinks there's nothing wrong with it.
他也覺得也不是什麼錯啊
As a result
結果因為這樣
Because we have a lot of internet police
因為我們有很多網路的警察
It's over because of this
因為這樣所以放完了
these have the case
這些有這個案子
There are these cases
有這些案例
But after he broke the law
可是他後來犯了法之後
Also know that he is 18 years old
還知道說他已經18歲了
he is an adult
他已經成年了
so this is unfair
所以這個很冤枉
Then this part is what we want
那這個部分就是我們要
always pay attention
隨時要去注意
sometimes we see
有時候我們看到
This problem with many cybercriminals
很多網路犯罪的這種問題
it hurts so much
就很心痛就是這樣
He didn't mean to commit a crime at all.
他根本就是不是刻意要去犯罪
like now we mentor graduate students
像現在我們指導研究生
Where is the most feared student
最怕的學生是在哪裡
Our advisors are also scared
我們當中指導教授也很怕
Because copypad is so convenient
因為copypad太方便了
They often inadvertently violate intellectual property
他們常常不小心就違反智慧財產
there will be that phenomenon of plagiarism
會有那個抄襲的現象
I copied the letter, this has to be dealt with
我抄取的信項,這個都要去處理的
So I said, how to avoid cybercrime
所以我說,網路犯罪如何避免
information literacy
也變成是一個資訊素養裡面
very important part
非常重要的一個部分
So this is also worthy of our discussion
所以這個也值得我們去做一個探討
Ok, so I put some applied themes
好,那我把一些應用的主題
make a very simple explanation
做一個很簡單的一個說明
First, the establishment and attack of digital learning environments
第一個,數位學習環境的建制跟攻擊
We want to build a digital learning environment
我們要建置一個數位學習的環境
Digital learning environments now probably have many
數位學習環境現在大概有很多
E-Learning platform, E-Learning platform
E-Learning的平台,E-Learning平台
Now the most popular is the future classroom
現在最流行的是未來教室
That is to say, the classroom in the future
就是說以後的教室
full of a
充滿了一種
For example, touch screen, electronic pendulum
譬如說觸摸式的螢幕、電子擺板
There are various resources over there, right?
那有各種資源在那邊,對不對
How to do this teaching
那這個怎麼來做教學
How to teach on this platform
就這個平台怎麼來做教學
The teacher almost had to re-believe
那老師幾乎要重新信念
Faith how to use this platform
信念怎麼利用這個平台
The content in it, how to design your teaching content
那裡面的內容,你的教學內容怎麼來設計
How to design, this must be considered
怎麼來設計,這個都是必須要考
there is another
另外還有一個
The current camp terminal in this digital platform
這種數位平台裡面現在的營端
We often go to the camp to calculate
我們常常到營端計算
Camp platform
營端的平台
If the camp terminal platform is really complete, it will really affect
營端平台如果真的完整之後真的會影響
A problem with many education in Taiwan
台灣很多教育的一個問題
For example, inside the camp
譬如說營端裡面
many of his software
他的很多軟體
All belong to APP, this kind of software is not big
都是屬於APP的這種軟體不大
That software doesn't do much
那軟體的功能不多
so later
所以以後
If this develops to a certain stage
如果這個發展到某個階段的話
It is very likely that when you learn certain information through the camp terminal
很有可能你透過營端去學習某一些資料的時候
fragments of your knowledge
你的知識會片段
This is a piece of knowledge
這是一個片段式的知識
So is there any sequelae when this is a fragment?
那這是片段的時候有沒有後遺症產生
A knowledge restructuring ability of students may be more important
學生的一種知識重組能力可能又更為重要
more important
更為重要
effects like this
類似這個的影響
will be more and more
會越來越多
The trend of technological development is irreversible
那科技發展的趨勢是不可導的
But in the whole process of technological development, it will cause the problem of technological hindrance
但是科技整個發展的過程裡面它會造成科技阻礙的問題
hinder the development of other fields
阻礙其他領域的發展
Then we all have to pay attention to this, so the platform
那這個我們都必須要去注意這個所以平台
Then there is this platform because there is a platform
那有這個平台因為有平台
So our study
所以我們的學習
Identification of the community
的認定 community
i learn to shoot
我學習射請
This human soul community always experiences
這個這個人靈community 總是經驗
So some teachers can use the human spirit community
所以有的老師可以透過人靈community
Gather the power of many other students
集合很多其他學生的力量
to tutor students
來輔導學生
There is also doing
也有這樣的做
so well done
所以做得好
It really helps a lot
的確是可以幫助很大
but you can't do well
可是你做不好
there may be many problems
可能就會有很多問題
What kind of students does the Human Soul community treat?
像人靈community對哪一些學生
very helpful
很有幫助
This is a result of some research
這都有一些研究的一個成果
Very helpful for the kind of shy student
對那種害羞的學生很有幫助
our often shy students
我們常常害羞的學生
He dare not interact with people
他不敢跟人家互動
He dare not ask a question
他也不敢發表問題
right
對不對
dare not express an opinion
不敢發表意見
But you through this kind of networking
但是你透過這種網路化的一種
When the soul community
人靈community的時候
Because he won't face to face
因為他不會跟人家面對面
face to face
實際面對面
he through the Internet
他透過網路
he can make a good interaction
他就可以做很好的一個互動
make good interaction
做很好的互動
so this part
所以這個部分
From a certain point of view, his academic achievement will be improved
對他的學習成就從某個角度是會提高的
So have one like this
所以有類似這樣子的一個
So the establishment of this whole learning environment is
所以這一個整個學習環境的建立是
more and more complicated
越來越複雜
and more and more
而且越來越可
that now
那現在
In universities, like Normal University, there are about 60% of the teachers
在大學裡面,像師大大概有60%的老師
Multiple digital learning platforms
多上數位學習平台
But digital learning platforms are not the only ones
但是數位學習平台不是唯一的啊
which means we teach
就是說我們教學
The interaction between people is still very important
人跟人之間的一個互動還是非常重要的
we can't ignore
我們不能夠忽略掉
A brainstorming question between people
人跟人之間的一種腦力激盪的問題
Not only through the Internet platform
不能夠只有透過網路的平台
So now the network platform has slowly developed into
所以現在網路平台已經慢慢發展成為
A study of the so-called Blenderland powder layer
所謂的Blenderland粉層式的一個學習
at a certain stage
就在某一個階段
There must be a face-to-face communication between the teacher and the students
一定要老師跟學生之間面對面的一個溝通
Internet-based processing at some stages of learning
在某一些學習階段透過網路來處理
For example, let me squeeze an example
譬如說我擠一個例子好了
Let's talk about the relationship between the nine planets and the sun
我們說那個九大行星跟太陽之間的關係
The relationship between the nine planets and the sun
那九大行星跟太陽之間的關係
We know that the earth rotates and revolves
我們知道地球有自轉也有公轉
But this is very abstract
但是這個都是很抽象的
very abstract for students
對學生而言都很抽象的
So how do you take the abstraction and turn it into
那你怎麼把抽象把它變成
I can do it easily through the computer
我那個透過電腦就很容易做
Otherwise you have to make an actual model
不然你就要做一個實際的模型
I let the students watch
我讓學生去看
I'll use a simpler example
我再用一個更簡單的例子
There is a teacher in our school
我們學校有一個老師
I heard that he used to teach like this
聽說他以前教書就這樣
I'm of course taking the simpler example
我當然以更簡單的例子
Let's say you teach that kindergarten student
譬如說你教那個幼稚園的學生
Then you have to teach what a pig is
然後你要教什麼是豬
right
對不對
It is very likely that students do not
那很有可能學生根本
he has never seen a pig
他從來沒有看過豬
so pigs may be very abstract to him
所以豬對他而言可能是很抽象的
right
對不對
It is very memorable for the teacher
對老師而言是很記憶的
You said this pig is very memorable
你講這個豬是很記憶的
But it is very abstract for students
可是對學生而言是很抽象的
he may not know what a pig is
他可能不知道什麼是豬
how do you teach
那你要怎麼教學
so sometimes the best way
所以有時候最好的方法
just do what you teach
就做什麼教學
Then the teacher plays the pig for the students to see
那就老師扮演豬給學生看
it becomes a memory
那就變成記憶的
is that impossible
那是可不可能
impossible
不可能嘛
So through multimedia
所以透過多媒體
I help you through online multimedia
我透過網路多媒體的方式來幫
So something like this
所以有類似這個
It's because he used to have a teacher named psychology
是他以前有一個叫心理學的老師
he often talks
他常常要講
A Mental Change in the Monkey
猴子的一個心理的變化
So I often play the role of a monkey for sacrifices
所以常常扮演猴子給犧牲看
right, that will make it clearer
對不對 那就會更清楚了
so something like this
所以類似這樣
Not many teachers like that know how to sacrifice
像那一種老師懂得犧牲的也不多
So what do you do, you have to do it through Domati
所以你只好怎麼辦 只好透過Domati
let the computer sacrifice
讓電腦來犧牲
Something like this, so the computer itself has a
類似這樣 所以電腦本身有一個
A very important part is
非常重要的一個部分是
what can he play poses
他可以扮演什麼戲 扮演姿勢
Valence's role
音價的角色
You mean the gestures and voices he plays through the computer
你就是說 他透過電腦所扮演的姿勢音價
Some abstract ideas that make sacrifices clearer
讓犧牲可以更清楚的一些抽象的觀念
better understanding of abstract concepts
更加理解抽象的觀念
Then it can be built on this platform
那這個平台裡面都可以建立起來
Another one is
另外還有一個是
tools for learning activities
學習活動的工具
Now we have to develop a lot of learning activities
現在我們要發展非常多的學習活動
Many things, what we call
很多東西 這個我們所謂
Editing tools for All-Sold-In-Two textbooks
All-Sold-In-Two 教材的編輯工具
Editing tools for learning activities
學習活動的編輯工具
Then how to design this
那這個 怎麼把它設計出來
We call it the intersectional design tool
我們把它叫做交學設計工具
how do you script
你怎麼做腳本
Lesson plan How to integrate with resources on the Internet
教案 那怎麼做整合 跟網路上的資源
Integrate it, an evolution of this tool
把它整合起來 那這個工具的一個發展
There are also interfaces and tools that facilitate human-computer interaction
另外還有促進人機互動的界面跟工具
this is very important this current development
這個很重要 這個目前的發展
more and more complicated more and more complicated
越來越複雜 越來越複雜
I was talking about augmented reality, right?
我剛才講的擴增實境 對不對
take reality take your real reality
把實境 把你真正的實境
Then amplify it with some information
再把它擴增一些信息出來
that you can achieve better human-machine interaction
那你可以達到更好的人機互動的一個問題
Then there's that mental reality, too.
那還有那個心靈實境 也是一樣
If you watch TV or watch movies
你如果看電視 看電影的話
you brought a universe
你帶了一個乾坤
When you stretch in the universe
當你乾坤那裡所謂伸進去之後
into the computer world
就可以伸到電腦的世界裡面
then you act as an electron
那你就扮演一個電子
or act as a computer's current
或者扮演一個電腦的電流
find information everywhere
到處去找資料
attract that reality
把那一種實境把它吸引化
It's all about the human-machine interface.
這個都是人機界面的問題
But where is the big problem of the man-machine interface now?
但是人機界面現在一個很大的問題在哪裡
Currently very troublesome three drops
目前很麻煩三滴
I have three drops now
我現在三滴
Why is three drops so troublesome
三滴為什麼很麻煩
If you don't usually touch three drops
各位如果平常不接觸三滴的時候
if you just watch the three drops movie
如果你就看三滴電影
There are a lot of people who really get dizzy
有很多人真的會頭昏腦臟
I really do
我真的會這樣
Because we have never had such a belief since childhood
因為我們從小沒有這樣的一個信念
And the three drops themselves
而且三滴本身
often when not handled well
常常在處理不好的時候
There will also be learning disabilities
還會有學習上的後遇症
there will be learning
會有學習上的
you just can't concentrate
就是你根本沒有辦法專注
i can't focus at all
我根本沒有辦法專注
Similar to this problem came out
類似這個問題就出來了
don't say anything
不要說什麼好
do this briefing
做這種簡報好了
It's easy for me to do this briefing, isn't it?
我做這個簡報還很簡單對不對
someone does this briefing
有人做這種簡報
In order to increase the effect of human-computer interaction
為了要增加人機互動的效果
Then there's a butterfly flying around
然後就有一隻蝴蝶在那飛來飛去
right
對不對
effect?
做效果嘛
and every time it comes out
然後每次一出來的時候
The word "it" is used to run in.
它這個字都用顯轉的跑進來
Is it this way
是不是這樣
then sometimes
然後有時候
Then one more word fell down
然後還有一個字一個字掉下來
so again
又這樣嘛
the scariest thing is
最可怕的是
When the word fell down, there was still that killer body
這個字掉下來的時候還有那個殺車身
right
對不對
isn't it scary
是不是很可怕
I see a lot of teachers in the past
我看很多以前很多老師
Just started to be a self-confident farmer
剛開始做自信農路家
Those teachers will be scolded by me
那些老師都會被我罵
why did i say two hours
為什麼我說兩個小時
or after two hours of class
或上課上完兩個小時之後
You still have this kind of display.
你還有這種顯轉進來的啦
Then there is that word running down
然後還有那個字跑下來
And kill the car
還有殺車身啦
I said it's no wonder that student didn't go crazy
我說那個學生不瘋掉才怪
Really, you can try it
真的各位可以試看看啦
right
對不對
really going crazy
真的會瘋掉
and more multimedia
而且多媒體越多
more severe cognitive load
造成認知負載越嚴重
What does cognitive load mean
認知負載是什麼意思
because we have a short-term memory
因為我們有一個短期記憶體
that short term memory
那短期記憶體
At the same time, the information that can be accepted is limited
同時可以接受的資訊是有限的
if you take many words at the same time
如果你同時接受很多的話
that's going to be a problem
那就會出問題
then i will
那我就
why butterflies
為什麼要蝴蝶
what does this butterfly have to do with this
這蝴蝶跟這有什麼關係
why do you want a butterfly to fly around
你為什麼要一隻蝴蝶飛來飛去
disturb us
干擾我們
right
對不對
really capable
能力真的喔
There are only two commonly used media
常用的媒體就只有兩個媒體了
One is called vision and the other is called hearing
一個叫做視覺,一個叫聽覺
right
對不對
Then the vision comes in and goes to the short-term memory of the vision
然後視覺進來之後會到視覺的短期記憶體
When hearing comes in, it goes to auditory short-term memory
聽覺進來的時候會到聽覺的短期記憶體
These two signals must interact
這兩個信號一定要交互作用
an interaction
一個交互作用
Then if after the interaction
那如果交互作用之後
you'll put the result in long-term memory
你就會把結果放在長期記憶體
then you write something
那你就寫到東西了
but we are not now
但是我們現在不是啊
Look at our multimedia
我們的多媒體你看
That you look doesn't match your voice
那個你看著跟你的聲音是不一致的
The two have no way to interact
兩個沒有辦法交互作用
At the same time you are viewing too much data at the same time
同時你同時看的資料太多
There are animations, texts, and pictures
有動畫啦,有文字啦,有圖片啦
The same picture is presented for you to see
同一個畫面呈現出來,讓你去看
So that all caused serious after-effects.
所以那個都造成很嚴重的後遺症
really all distractions
真的都是分心
You can do experiments when you go back.
各位回去可以做實驗看看
This multimedia experiment is scary
這個多媒體實驗是很可怕的
For example, if you drive a car, one day you will be able to drive
譬如說你開車,有一天你開車好了
we have men who can drive
我們有男士可以開車
Then you ask your wife to fish for you by the side
然後你叫你太太在旁邊給你撈刀
How much did the stock drop today?
撈刀今天股票跌多少
I don't believe traffic will be safe
我就不相信交通會開的會很安全
Thanks
謝謝
disturbed
被干擾
because you see
因為你看到的
road condition
路況的狀況
inconsistent with what your wife said
跟你太太所講的是不一致的
right
對不對
there will be problems
會有問題
Let's squeeze another example why we punish students
我們再擠一個例子我們為什麼要處罰學生
Now when students are punished, they are often accused, right? I just learned
現在處罰學生常常會被告啊對不對我就剛我們學
Why do you punish students for moving around and the defendant is sometimes sued by parents and children
你幹嘛處罰學生動不動被告有時候被家長告被小孩告
Is it true that the private relationship has not been done well?
對不對私生關係又沒有弄好
So it's very simple to punish students, don't scold him, don't beat him
所以處罰學生就很簡單嘛你也不要罵他不要打他很簡單
I will change Mr. Hu
我就把胡導師改一下
Strong and bad all in white
強弊全部都用白色的
Right? Then the student stood there and all he saw was white.
對不對然後學生就站在那邊他看的全部都是白色的
Then you just sit in front and give him two hours
然後你就坐在前面給他拉到兩個小時
I can't see the skinny
看到瘦的了瘦不了
Right? What he saw was completely inconsistent with what he heard.
對不對他看了跟聽了完全不一致
what's the use of hitting him
你打他有什麼用
Because you beat a student, he is young and he can recover easily
因為你打學生他年輕他很容易恢復啊
Right? Then you are older, your cells after beating him
對不對那你年紀比較大打他之後你的細胞
and easy
又很容易
lost
喪失掉
Then your students are all recovered
然後你的學生都恢復好了
so you just don't
所以你乾脆就不要
I'll just find a room called Fukushima City
我就把一個找一間那個叫做福島市
Do not stick anything on the long arm
長臂通通不要貼任何東西
Give him 70% white
全部給他七成白色的
But what he saw was a white wall
但他看了就是白色的牆壁
Then you talk to him about the things he's least interested in.
那你就跟他談他最沒有興趣的事情
After talking to him for an hour and two hours
給他談了一個小時兩個小時之後
His ears create a cognitive load
他耳朵會造成認知負載
That's serious. You can try it when you go back.
那個很嚴重回去可以試看看
So parents can do the same
所以父母也可以這樣做
we have kids, right?
我們有小朋友對不對
you teach your parents
你教你的父母
make a kitchen with you
跟你這樣做一個廚房
guaranteed to be fun
保證很有趣
So there are really many tools that can be researched here.
所以這裡面可以研究的工具真的很多
really a lot
真的非常多
One piece of information you can explore is a lot
你們可以探討的一個資訊是很多的
I remember my son is very old now
我記得我兒子現在已經年紀很大了
we come back as soldiers
我們當完兵回來
I remember when he was in elementary school
我記得他那時候讀國小的時候
The elementary school was just doing that new dish
國小剛剛有在做那個新做盤
To see what's new
要看那個各種新做
So to practice new disk
所以要練習新做盤
Then we know that living in Taipei City
那我們知道住在台北市
can you see the stars at night
晚上看得到星星嗎
can't see it
看不到對不對
so i remember
所以我就記得
to do his homework
為了做他的作業
Then drive to that farm road in Keelung
然後開車到那個基隆的農道
Isn't there a farm road by the sea in Keelung?
基隆海邊不是有農道嗎
farm road and then
農道然後就
Use the horoscope chart with him to see various constellations
跟他用星座盤來看各種星座
various constellations
各種星座
After reading it, you must go at night
看完之後 一定要晚上去嘛
So when I got home, it was like 3 or 4 o'clock
所以回到家裡好像3、4點了
I really want to sleep like this
就很想睡 這樣睡
As a result, my son woke me up at 7 o'clock in the morning
結果早上7點就被我兒子叫起來
his dad sucks shit what...what did i say shit
他爸爸糟糕了 糟糕了怎麼...我說什麼糟糕
This is a constellation in the northern hemisphere, what about the southern hemisphere?
他這個是北半球的星座啊 南半就怎麼辦
i just want
我就想
What is the best teaching? Contextualized teaching?
最好的教學是什麼教學? 情境化的教學嘛
Right, go directly to the scene?
對不對 直接到現場去嘛
But how did you get to the southern hemisphere?
可是 你怎麼到南半球
It's hard, isn't it?
這很難嘛 對不對
So sometimes the textbook is really badly designed, right?
所以有時候那個教材實在設計不好 對不對
You can teach the northern hemisphere, but you are still teaching the southern hemisphere
你教北半球就好 偏偏還在教個南半球
And our parents don't know what to do
還有我們家長不知道怎麼辦
It's even more hateful. What kind of course is there?
更可惡 還有一種課程是什麼課程
Then watch the volcano explode.
那看火山爆花啦
Watching volcanic explosions, you need situational teaching
看火山爆花 你要情境教學
don't know how...how to teach
不知道怎麼...怎麼教咧
Why...why can't you take him to the next seat to have a look?
怎麼...怎麼不能把他帶到下位去看吧
So sometimes our situational teaching is
所以有時候我們的情境教學是
very good...both good teaching effect
非常好的...既有很好的教學效果
but often not feasible
但是常常不可行
Of course not feasible
當然不可行
Like I know you are in elementary school and junior high school
像我知道你們讀小學是國中
When you were in junior high school, did you observe your karma when you were in elementary school?
國中上 你讀小學的時候有沒有觀察業量
Is there, is there, right?
有沒有 有嘛 對不對
Every child must observe the karma
每一個小孩子都要觀察業量
But at that time everyone had neck problems
可是那一段時間每個人脖子都有問題
Just look up and look again, causing traffic problems again
就抬頭看再看 又引起交通問題
right? what should I do?
對不對 那怎麼辦
But where can you find the karma for 365 days a year?
可是一年365天的業量你到哪裡找
Are there any on the Internet? Yes, really.
網路上有沒有 有啊 真的有
A karma simulation of 365 days during that period
那一段時間365天的一種業量模擬
so many teachers find that site
所以有很多老師找到那個網站
Then give a lot of homework and ask them to analyze the changes in the entire karma
然後出很多作業 叫他們去分析整個業量的變化
This is the idea of ​​constructivism
這是建構主義的觀念啊
He doesn't tell you the answer
他不告訴你答案啊
Tell you to look at various karma to find out some relationships
叫你看各種業量去找出一些關係出來
So this is a lot, actually the human interface
所以這個就很多 其實人際界面
Very helpful for contextualized communication
對情境化交流是非常有幫助
very helpful that works well
非常有幫助 那個效果都很好
But I have a lot of opinions, every time I talk to some teachers
但是我很多意見 每次跟一些老師談
They are not willing to accept my good words
都不太願意接受我很好的看話
In fact, there are several examples
其實都有幾個例子好了
We often teach children
我們常常教小孩子
If you meet Shero
如果碰到社郎的時候
How should it be, right?
應該怎麼樣怎麼樣對不對
So the teacher will want to say on the blackboard
所以老師就會在黑板想說
when you meet the bad guys or the club
當你碰到壞人或碰到社郎的時候
what do you want first
第一個你要怎麼樣
what about the second one
第二個你要怎麼樣
What about the third one?
第三個你要怎麼樣
Is it like this
是不是這樣一交
But really, if one day we meet
可是真的萬一有一天碰到的話
what will happen to this student
這個學生會怎麼樣
nothing can happen
什麼都不能怎麼樣
Because he cuts out the chance to practice
因為他切少練習機會
right
對不對
But is this kind of practice possible for him?
可是這種是能夠讓他練習嗎
no way
不行嘛
how can you get these people to practice
你怎麼可以讓這些人去練習
Come back after practicing once
因為練習一次就回來
So I talked to many
所以我就跟很多
The middle school sex director said
國中那個性勞主任講說
Isn't our school building a lot of nature trails?
我們學校不是建立很多什麼自然步道嗎
the learning trail
那個學習步道嗎
Just as I said, why don't you make a club
正而我說你們為什麼不做一個社郎步道
Then let the general
然後讓總務
Let the sex director play the role of the club man
讓那個性勞主任扮演社郎
Give students the opportunity to practice
讓學生有練習的機會
right
對不對
How good is it to achieve the purpose of situational teaching
達到情境教學的目的多好
But they don't seem to want
可是他們好像都不太願意
stay away from my opinion
離我這個意見
I think I'm still strong
我覺得我到現在還是結實
this opinion is good
這個意見是不錯的
But they are not willing to accept
可是他們就不太願意接受
very strange
很奇怪
I said, then you take turns to do it.
我說那你就輪著做嘛
Don't trust the old director every time, right?
不要每次都信老主任做嘛 對不對
You Lutheran Lord can do it too.
你信義主長也可以做啊
there is another
另外還有一個
Learning without Hu Shou
胡首不在的學習
This study without Hu Shou is a
這胡首不在的學習是一個
Future development because we learn from the effectiveness
未來發展 因為我們學習成效裡面
There are probably formal learning and informal learning
大概有formal learning跟informal learning
A kind of learning like school belongs to formal learning
一種像學校的學習是屬於formal learning
But informal learning is like a museum
但是informal learning像博物館
Moreover, in our general learning environment,
而且我們一般的整個學習的一個環境裡面
about seventy or eighty percent
大概百分之七八十
It's all about informal learning
都是跟informal learning有關
will formally learn about
會正規學習有關
But I will study formally
可是會正規學習裡面
For example, if you go to a museum to visit
譬如說你到博物館去參觀
can you really learn about all the artifacts in the museum
你是不是真的可以了解博物館所有的文物
can you help me
有沒有能夠幫你
So what do we often do
所以我們常常會怎麼
Will find a guide's energy to assist us, right?
會找一個導覽的能源來協助我們 對不對
action learning now
那現在行動學習
This has its advantage
這個就有它的一個好處在了
Have it to bring your navigating energy to you
有它可以把你的導覽能源帶到你
bring you
帶到你身邊
I bring you to deal with
我帶到你身邊來處理
that same same
那一樣同樣
Like that learning walk, I often say that there are many learning walks in schools now
像那個學習步道,我常常說現在學校有很多學習步道
The learning trail can also be used as a mobility vehicle
那學習步道也可以把行動載具
integrated into the learning trail
整合在學習步道裡面
you got somewhere
這都你到了某一個地方
He will show you some relevant information
他就會秀一些相關的資訊給你
Now in many elementary schools
現在在很多國小教育裡面
Isn't there an outdoor teaching association?
不是都有戶外教協嗎?
Doesn't the Outdoor Education Association have a study list? Right?
那戶外教協不是都有學習單嗎?對不對?
In the study sheet, there is a principle in the design of the study sheet
那在學習單,學習單的設計有一個原則
He hopes that through the topics in the worksheet
他是希望透過學習單裡面題目
To guide you to explore some information on the site
來引導你去探索現場的一些資料
Explore some plants in your outdoor teaching association as well
探索你的戶外教協的一些植物也好
animals too , i hope you explore
動物也好,我希望你去探索
So the design of that topic is very important
所以那個題目的設計是很重要
but in this whole
那但是在這個整個裡面
in the process of exploring
在探索的過程裡面
For example, you read a page
譬如說你看了一個頁子
If the student doesn't understand, he doesn't understand
這個學生看不懂就是看不懂
Because there are no information stations hidden in this page
因為這個頁子裡面沒有藏一些信息站
Can you understand what I mean? The page you read is just a page
能不能了解我的意思?頁子你看了就是一個頁子
Does it have any information in it?
它裡面有沒有一些資訊也沒有
What if you go through a mobile vehicle
怎麼辦呢 如果你透過行動載具的話
situational awareness
我們所謂的情境感知
What does situational awareness mean?
情境感知是什麼意思呢
when it gets there it will
它到那個地方它就會
Survive to sense
生存到 會感應到
After sensing it, it will take you this
感應到之後它就會把你這個
Information about this leaf
跟這個葉子有關的資料
will show up on your screen
會秀在你的螢幕上面
just provide some additional information
就提供一些額外的信息
additional information to help
額外的信息來幫助
So something like this
所以類似這樣子的一個作法
So it is very suitable for use in informal learning
所以它非常適合在非正式學習裡面使用
Also in formal learning
另外在正式學習裡面
also a very important
也一個很重要的
in trading theory
在交易理論
inside the trading theory
交易理論裡面
Our Hirara
我們的平良
There are two types of Hira
有兩大類平良
one called
一個叫做
One type of formation Taira
一種形成性平良
summative level
一個叫做總結性平良
What does formative goodness mean?
那形成性平良是什麼意思呢
that is
就是說
I hope that after this formative Hira
我希望透過這個形成性平良之後
Know what your current study status is
知道你目前的學習狀態是什麼
Then according to your study status
然後按照你的學習狀態呢
I will do remedial teaching
我來做補救教學
I am formative Hirao
我這個是形成性平良
That summative level
那總結性平良
So it’s because the pedestrian Xingping Liang is a very important role for half a year
所以在於裡面行人性平良是半年很重要的角色
But we're almost in a classroom in Taiwan
但是我們幾乎在台灣的教室裡面
Hirao
幾乎沒有行人性平良
why? we have a lot of quizzes
為什麼?我們有很多小考
Right? But after the quiz
對不對?可是小考考完之後
Does any teacher have time to read the results of the quiz
有哪個老師有時間去看小考的結果
Then judge which concept in the previous class is not understood
然後來判斷說前班裡面哪一個觀念是不懂的
He can only do well in the previous class
他只能夠做好這前班裡面
What is your average grade?
你的平均成績是多少?
He has no way to judge which concept in the previous class is not understood
他沒有辦法去判斷前班裡面哪個觀念是不懂
Because the teacher has no time
因為老師也沒有時間
So we only have quizzes
所以我們只有小考
We take the quiz as a summative level
我們把小考也當作總結性平良去做
so in the classroom
所以在教室裡面
If people, teachers, real people
如果以人、以老師實際的人
With the teaching mode like this with students
跟學生這樣的教學模式的話
There is probably no way to be a pedestrian
大概沒有辦法做到行人性平良
That is to say, there is almost no way for the teacher to know
就說老師幾乎沒有辦法知道
Which classmate or most of the classmates in the previous class
哪一個同學或前班大部分的同學
which idea is not understood
哪個觀念是不懂的
There's almost no way I can be pedestrian
我幾乎沒有辦法做到行人性平良
there is almost no way i can do it
我幾乎沒有辦法做到
that's an important part
那這個很重要的一個部分
Then this mobile vehicle can do that
那這個行動載具就可以做到這一點
because it can drop the title where
因為它可以把題目丟到哪個地方
Throw it into every man's mobile vehicle
丟到每一個人手的行動載具裡面
students can answer
學生可以去回答
Immediately after answering, collect them all
回答之後馬上全部收集起來之後
Can do data processing
可以做資料處理
can judge immediately
就馬上可以判斷
Which idea does the student not understand
學生哪個觀念不懂
you will fix it next time
你下一次就來補救
do remedial this instructable
做補救這個教學
like this
類似這樣
So this place can improve us a kind
所以這個地方就可以改善我們一種
A practice of Comoron Forest
科摩倫林的一個作法
like a museum is not real
像博物館就非真事寫行
when you visit a museum
你參觀博物館的時候
For example, we sometimes receive this
譬如說我們有時候會接到這個掌務
What is the characteristic of this management
這個掌務的特色是什麼
which dynasty
是哪一個朝代的
And what kind of special love story is there on his front?
然後他的正面有什麼樣的特殊情話
But one of the most important features of this management
可是這個掌務最重要的一種特色
is behind
是在背後
Do we now have a master that will automatically
我們現在有沒有掌務會自動
turn around to show you
轉到背後給你看
Won't
不會
right
對不對
So you pass through the mobile vehicle
所以你透過行動載具
information behind
就可以把背後的信息
render it into your vehicle
把它呈現到你的載具裡面
So a kind of mobility vehicle
所以行動載具的一種
action learning
這種行動學習
A very important part of this part is
這個部分有一個非常重要的一個部分是
human muscle
要把人肌
skin
肌
on the actual situation
就實際的情境
The interaction of the three brings it together
三者的互動把它整合在一起
integrate it
把它整合
this is the hardest part
這是最難做的一個部分
from a transactional point of view
就以交易的角度
How do we muscle people
我們怎麼把人肌肌
The three put it together
三者把它整合
it's difficult
這是很困難
How are you framing this transaction scenario?
你怎麼在設計這種交易的情境
so this place will
所以這個地方要
there is another one
另外還有一個就
Hu Shou is not in a learning digital content communication strategy and Pingliang method will change
胡首不在的一種學習的數位內容交協的策略跟平良方法會改變
because your screen is not big
因為你的螢幕不大
right so you can render the content at the same time
對不對所以你可以同時呈現的內容
is limited
是有限的
so how do you find effective content and present it
所以你怎麼找到有效的內容把它呈現出來
this is very complicated
這個是很複雜
there is another
另外還有一個
A very important one like our Pingliang
一個很重要像我們平良
There is a kind of Pingliang called Situation Pingliang
平良有叫做有一種平良叫情境平良
What is Pingjing Pingliang? For example, we
什麼叫做平境平良譬如說我們
us
我們
go to the entrance
去入口
right
對不對
Don't you need a driver's license to drive?
開車不是要拿駕照嗎
driver's license you need to go to the entrance
駕照你要到入口
The entrance test is that you actually go into the situation and then take the test.
那入考是你實際到情境裡面然後去考
You can judge after that
那考之後就可以判斷
This is called a good situation
這個叫做情境平良
In this peaceful environment
那這情境平良裡面
It is impossible to do it in a real educational environment.
在現實的一種教育環境裡面也是做不到
So how do you get through this mobility vehicle
那你如何透過這種行動載具
Achieving a goal of peace of mind
達到情境平良的一個目的
so hard to do
所以都很難做
I actually don't have many standard answers for this part
我這個部分事實上也沒有很多標準的答案
I'm all constantly
我目前大家都一直不斷的
I'll go and find out
我再去做一個了解
I do a find out what exactly is
我做一個了解到底是
what should be done better
應該怎麼做會比較好
Then there is another one
那另外還有一個就是說
Then how do I evaluate his learning effect?
那我怎麼去評估他的學習效果
And he applied the whole process
還有他應用整個歷程
did you record it for me
有沒有幫我把它記錄下來
Also the design of your entire event
另外你整個活動的設計
Learning in action throughout
在整個行動學習
Design of the whole event
整個活動的設計
The result of this design
這個設計的結果
How do you evaluate whether he is good or not?
你怎麼去評估他好不好
i evaluate him
我評估他
he is right or wrong
他對還是錯
Then assess whether he is motivated to learn?
那評估他是不是有學習動機
right
對不對
a situation like this
像類似這樣子的一個情況
Don't think that sometimes mobile vehicle design is too fun
各位不要以為有時候行動載具設計太好玩
Strong motivation to learn
學習動機很強
but his learning motivation
但他學習動機
Where are you so strong? So strong because this loading technique is fun
你強勢強在哪裡?強到因為這個載技很好玩
not your content is fun
不是你的內容很好玩
So your final learning effect is not good
所以你最後的學習效果也不好
Therefore, being motivated to learn does not mean that there is a learning effect.
所以有學習動機並不表示有學習效果
Because your loading skills are so interesting
因為你的載技是太有意思了
like gamified learning
就好像遊戲化的學習
right?
對不對?
Gamified learning is done well
遊戲化學習是做得好
is really hard to do
是真的很難做
You have both the function of the game and the effect of learning
你既有遊戲的功能而且又有學習的效果
really hard to do
真的是非常難做
I've only seen one so far and probably nothing else.
我目前看到大概只有一個而已其他大概都沒有
We all play games now, right? It’s fun, isn’t it?
我們現在遊戲都打打殺殺對不對都很好玩對不對
But there is no learning effect
可是有沒有學習效果也沒有
Therefore, learning is a kind of learning software design based on games.
所以學習化就以遊戲為主的一種學習的軟體的設計
is hard to design
是很難設計的
Well, but if your design is successful
那但是如果你設計很成功的話
that would be a big deal
那就不得了了
We know that there are many kinds of nurturing
我們知道有很多一種養成
It is difficult to develop a
有一種養成是很困難的
We make it a value development
我們把它成為一種價值觀的養成
develop an attitude
跟態度的養成
is hard
是很難的
Everyone has different values
每一個人有每一個人不同的價值觀
So you're going to change a person's politics
所以你要改變一個人政治
a political or religious belief
政治的一種或宗教的信仰
is hard
是很難的
Sometimes education is not enough
有時候教育的手段都做不到
so it's hard for you to change it
所以你要改變它很難
I remember
那我記得喔
a few years ago, about ten years ago, ten years ago
在好幾...大概十年前來十幾年前
there was a survey
那時候有一個調查
Investigation seems to be idol pair
調查好像是偶像對
A Survey of Human Idols
對人類偶像的調查
As a result, the politicians came to the back
結果政治人物盤到後面
Who is the number one, do you know?
排第一名是誰各位知不知道
Cao Cao
曹操
Why is Cao Cao ranked first?
為什麼排第一名曹操呢
Because at that time there was a game software
因為那個時候有一個遊戲軟體
About the game software of Romance of the Three Kingdoms
就三國志的遊戲軟體
very smart
非常聰明
and he's cosplaying
而且他是做角色扮演
you can play cao cao
你可以扮演曹操
Play Liu Bei and play anything
扮演劉備扮演什麼都可以扮演
As a result, he changed one of his ideas
結果他改變他的一種觀念
change his attitude
改變他的態度
so it's hard
所以這很難
Being able to design this kind of game can make money
能夠設計到這種遊戲可以賺錢
another change of mind
又可以改變一個想法
is also very difficult
也是很困難
To change a concept through which place
要改變一個觀念透過哪個地方
cooperative game
合作式的遊戲
So I work with a group of people through cooperation
所以說我透過合作跟一組人來共同
to solve a certain difficulty of the game
來解決某一個遊戲的難關之後
that might change your values
那可能會改變你的價值觀
So the interaction between people is very important
所以人跟人的互動是很重要
you teach honestly
你用老實去教
to try to change his political stance
要嘗試改變他的政治立場
try to change his religion
嘗試改變他的宗教信仰
it's actually hard
事實上是很難的
But if a body
但是如果一個情體
It is possible to change after a long time
經過一個長時間之後是有可能改變
so this place
所以這個地方
So this part of the evaluation method is difficult to do
所以這個部分的評估方法是很難做的
Now our general education assessment method
現在我們一般的教育的評估方法
probably several
大概有幾種
Generally, there are quantitative methods and value analysis
一般有量的方法跟值的分析
Quantitative method, we use experimental group, control group, etc.
量的方法我們就實驗組 控制組等等
then compare
然後去做比較
The value analysis we have to do
那值的分析我們要做
take a picture of its information
把它的資料把它攝影下來
We'll do tape analysis after the filming
攝影下來我們做錄音帶分析
tape analysis
錄音帶分析
See how his behavior changes
看他行為的變化是什麼樣
this can be done
這都可以做
Now there is old science
那現在有老科學的
an application to education
一種應用到教育裡面
also doing
也有在做
But the question is now what
可是問題現在這個怎麼樣
This action learning is
這種行動學習是
I don't know where the students go
是學生跑到哪裡就不知道
Like we used to do action learning in museums
像我們也曾經有做博物館的行動學習
that's hard work
那個很辛苦耶
First
第一個
Because they are all elementary school students
因為都是小學生嘛
So we're afraid he'll drop our tablet on the ground
所以我們怕他把我們的平板電腦掉到地下
We can't blame him for falling into the ground and ruining it.
掉到地下又毀了我們又不能怪他
So we specially designed a bag to drop here
所以我們就特別要去設計一個袋子掉到這裡
Let him stay like this even if he falls
讓他即使掉了還是在脖子這樣
fall over there
掉到那一邊
but we have to collect him
可是我們要收集他
collect his information
收集他的資料啊
Is that right? Collect his information and write that we sometimes don’t know each other.
對不對那收集他的資料寫成我們有時候不認識
So I had to make another hat, this is student No. 1, student No. 2
所以只好再去做一個帽子這是1號學生這2號學生
make lots of hats for them to put on their heads
做很多帽子給他們戴到頭上
Then we start designing
然後我們先就開始設計
design
設計
But sometimes they talk
可是他們有時候會在討論啊
I can't hear the discussion sometimes.
討論有時候聽不到啊
so again
所以又要
Are you going to use that hidden microphone again?
又要用那個什麼隱藏式麥克風
Because I can't let them know that there is a microphone
因為又不能夠讓他們知道說有麥克風齁
they started not to speak
他們就開始不敢講話
hidden microphone
隱藏式麥克風
But I want to see the expression on his face
可是又希望看到他的面部的表情
So I had to add one to the mobile vehicle
所以只好在行動載具裡面加一個
CAMERA
CAMERA
I design
我就設計
so complicated
所以很複雜啊
It was hard work, it was hard work to do that experiment.
很辛苦啊做那個實驗都很辛苦
spend a lot of money
花很多錢
But this way of evaluating
但是這種評估的方法
indeed in action
的確是在行動
ubiquitous learning inside
無所不在的學習裡面
is a complicated part
是複雜了一個部分
It is also necessary to conduct a discussion
也需要去做一個探討
In addition, there is a digital content application guide
另外還有一個數位內容應用的導向
The first online learning resource
第一個網路學習資源
This learning resource is very important
這個學習資源是蠻重要的
For example, the current simulation software
譬如說現在的模擬化的軟體
We put a lot of abstract things
我們把很多抽象的東西
Design through simulation software
透過模擬軟體的設計
simulate on the computer
在電腦上面做模擬
electric second wave
電秒算波
And the learning simulation has an important part
而且學習的模擬有一個很重要的部分
The simulation of the game is different
遊戲的模擬不一樣
Like many gamification software nowadays, it is simulation
像現在很多遊戲化軟體是模擬
you become a mayor
你當一個市長
or you are a government
或者你是一個政府
then how do you build a city
然後你怎麼蓋一個城市
So that software is complicated
所以那個軟體很複雜
The software we trade with is not that complicated
我們交易的軟體沒有那麼複雜
Why? Because I just talked about the concept of scaffolding
為什麼?因為我剛才講了鷹架的觀念
That is to say I can start from the simple pattern
就是說我可以從簡單的模式
tell you the result
告訴你這個結果
Then slowly add the complex
然後慢慢把複雜的加進來
So we don't start by putting the most complex situation in
所以我們不是一開始就把最複雜的情境擺進來
Instead, gradually add complexity
而是逐步的把複雜加進來
So the simulation is a simplified simulation of
所以模擬是經過簡化的一個模擬
Sometimes it works better
有時候反而是效果更好的
If game software it's full emulation
如果遊戲軟體它是完整的模擬
sometimes it doesn't work
那有時候效果是不好的
So there's just too much to do in one design
所以這裡面的一個設計有太多要做的部分
There is too much of a learning karma
有太多一種學習之業
Now Silverside itself is your learning software
現在銀端本身你的學習軟體
put your resources on
你的資源放在上面
Is there any change in the part of your presentation?
那你的呈現的部分有沒有什麼改變
How to manage this place effectively
這個地方都要去如何做有效的一個管理
Then how to do an effective presentation
然後如何做有效的呈現
In addition, in the wireless network
另外在無線化 網路化
In the case of a mobile carrier
還有行動載機的情況底下
Can these learning contents be cross-platform?
那這些學習內容能不能夠跨平台
Something like this has to be dealt with
類似這個都要去處理
Then this one is and the other one is information technology
那這個是還有一個是資訊科技
Integrate into teaching and learning
融入教學跟學習這個部分
this part
這個部分
we have less time
我們時間比較少啦
But it's an important place
不過也是蠻重要的一個地方
Well, Taiwan has implemented it for more than ten years.
那這個台灣已經實施了十幾年了
So teachers have many ways to use
所以老師有很多都有辦法利用
Intellectual Technology In fact, all tools can do
知性科技 事實上所有工具都可以做
all tools can do
所有工具都可以做
For example, you can teach simple statistics with Xare
譬如說你用 Xare 可以教簡單的統計
teachers can use
老師都可以用
I just remember a teacher who was very good at them
我就記得一個老師很厲害他們那個
Teaching for him to teach statistics
教學的做 他為了教統計
teach students statistics and then
教學生統計 然後
Then he started to design
然後他就開始設計出來
he's the first he wants to get motivated
他第一個他要引起動機
How does he arouse motivation? He puts a lot of information
他引起動機怎麼做 他就把一大堆信息
Messy and show on PowerPoint
很亂的然後秀在 PowerPoint 上面
Then ask the students, what is the relationship between these numbers?
然後就問學生說 請問這些數字有什麼關係
That student must not understand
那學生一定搞不清楚
I don't know what's the matter
不知有什麼關係
He said that I will change the mode for you
他說那我變一個模式給你好了
and then after clicking
然後按一下之後
After pressing it, the numbers will start to run slowly
按一下之後 然後就開始慢慢這些數字就會跑
Run into a statistical result
跑成一個統計的結果
Then you say what's the relationship
然後你說這個是什麼關係
written achievement is very clear
寫成就很清楚
he just for motivation
他只是為了講引起動機
For students interested in statistics
對學生對統計有興趣
He does such a treatment
他就做這樣的一個處理
There is another one who doesn't know there are children here
還有一個不知道這邊有小孩子
I don't know if I should talk
不知道應不應該講
Then don't take me as the principal of the Normal University
那個你就不要把我當作師大校長
it caused me to talk about the professor
就引起我講教授
Because the president of the normal university sometimes
因為師大校長有時候
more responsibilities
背負的責任都比較大
This is actually the problem
這個事實上是這一個問題
In fact, there are teachers who teach
事實上是有老師這樣教
don't we have sex education
我們不是有性教育嗎
right
對不對
How about sex education
那性教育怎麼教
And he's talking about animal sex
而且他還要講動物的性行為
I don't know why there is such a class
我不曉得為什麼有這種課
It's really the teacher who teaches like this
真的是那個老師就這樣教
how does he do you know
他怎麼做你知道
He was just at that time
他就剛剛好那個時候
Discovery
Discovery
He has a company for his videos
他就把他的影片有一家公司
Buy the rights to Discovery
買到Discovery的版權
That copyright can be picked up segment by segment
那那個版權是可以把一段一段的撿起來
It's not the whole film, it's picked up piece by piece
不是整片是一段一段的撿起來
then put it on the web
然後就放在網路上
Then he put the sexual behavior of animals in Discover
然後他就把 Discover 裡面跟動物的性行為有關的
Then hand it over to sketch in class
然後就在課堂裡面交給寫生
Let Sketchbook understand this essay question
讓寫生了解這個論文問題
Then you say there is no video, how can we teach it?
那你說這個沒有影片我們怎麼教啊
There is no way to actually operate it.
也沒辦法實際操作啊
Right, it’s hard, right, it’s really hard
對不對 很難啊 對不對 真的很難啊
But there is such a course
可是真的有這種課程啊
But I saw that he was very natural after teaching.
可是我看他教完之後就非常的自然
very natural
非常的自然
Therefore, in fact, many media
所以也說其實很多媒體
Always felt a need to have a lot to teach
總是覺得很多要教的東西是必要性
but very embarrassing
可是非常尷尬
But after going through the media, it became normal
可是透過媒體之後就變得很正常
become normal, something like this
變得很正常 類似這樣子的一個做法
So the teacher will also do this
所以老師也會做這個
so they can find many
所以他們可以找到很多個
I also saw a teacher
我還有看過一個老師
I've asked many people what to do
我到現在也問過很多人應該怎麼做
There was an earthquake at that time, right?
那時候剛好有地震吧
He's going to teach that tremor
他就要教那個震度
How strong is the vibration of your earthquake?
你地震的震動那個震度有多
he did it for the first time
他就做第一次
How about the earthquake in the first episode, it's moving on the screen
第一集的地震怎麼樣 螢幕上就在動
How did you move in the first episode? How did you move in the second episode? Move even more
第一集怎麼動 第二集怎麼動 動得更厲害
By the end of the episode, the screen broke
到最後一集的時候 螢幕就破掉了
If you want to move until it breaks, you have to simulate it completely
要動到破掉 完全都要模擬
It must be simulated completely. There is also such a method
完全都要模擬 也有這樣的一個做法
So this is very interesting, and in fact our domestic
所以這個是很有趣的 而且其實我們國內的
Teacher Zhuang Xiaoyi's ability in this area is usually pretty good
莊小儀老師這方面的能力 平常都還不錯
Our teacher is quite serious
我們老師算還是蠻認真的
just because it's a pity
只是因為比較可惜什麼
Most of this is done by elementary school teachers.
這個大部分都是國小老師完成的
Because he doesn't have the entrance exam pressure, he doesn't have the entrance exam
因為他沒有聯考壓力 他沒有聯考
I also saw an example
我還有看過一個例子
a music teacher
一個音樂老師
because he was going to teach that
因為他要教那個
It seems that the elementary school plays the flute or the tendons
好像國小不是有吹笛子 還是吹筋筋
But every time I play the flute
可是每次吹笛子的時候
Because the piano teacher needs an accompaniment, right?
因為鋼琴老師要伴奏 對不對
Only the body of the shoe can play the flute
那鞋身才能夠吹笛子
But he said that every time we were playing the accompaniment
可是他說我們每次在伴奏的時候
I really do not know
我真的不知道
How about the students blowing
到學生吹了怎麼樣
He really doesn't know because he's playing the accompaniment
他真的不知道 因為他在伴奏
But then it was very simple, he just used a computer
但後來就很簡單 他就用一部電腦
Then he asked the computer to do the accompaniment
然後他要伴奏的事情交給電腦做
So the computer is playing the accompaniment and he listens to it one by one
所以電腦在伴奏 然後他就一個一個去聽
So the computer becomes his assistant
所以電腦變成他的助手
My assistant went to play the accompaniment and he listened to them one by one
我助手去伴奏 然後他就一個一個去聽聽他們
How about blowing the bottom? It's a music teacher's job.
底子吹了怎麼樣 這是一個音樂老師做
So in other words, there are actually a lot of creative ways
所以也就是說 其實有很多創意的做法
It actually exists in our teaching environment
在我們教學環境裡面事實上是存在的
It's also quite a conscious approach.
也是蠻有意識的一個做法
I used to teach calligraphy. Our Dean Wang Hu is a calligrapher.
以前有教書法 我們王沪院長是書法家
I heard that calligraphy must be the first to draw red
聽說書法一定要第一個要描紅
step by step
一步一步來
That teacher, he is very good
那一個老師他就 他很厲害
He wrote it himself first and then asked someone to take a picture of it
他就自己先寫 然後找人家把它攝影下來
After shooting, in that step
攝影下來之後 在那個步驟裡面
he put it
他就把它
play it out
把它play出來
he uses media play
他用media play
Then media play can repeat
那media play又可以repeat
So the same comparison he kept
所以同樣一比 他就不斷地
My fart let the students watch
我裏屁的讓學生看
I let the students see how he wrote
我讓學生看他是怎麼寫的
I keep showing him
我一直不斷的給他看
If you were to teach yourself how
如果你要自己教你怎麼
i remember when i was young
我記得我小時候
The teacher taught us to write with a brush, right?
老師教我們寫毛筆是用魂筆在寫對不對
a soul pen and draw again
一隻魂筆然後再畫
that can't be done at all
那根本沒辦法做
So there are also teachers who do it specially.
所以也有老師專門做的
So this is an auxiliary tool and it is also very effective.
所以這個都是一種輔助工具也是滿有效的
There is also a kind of university
另外還有一個大學的一種
Especially now that the general education courses in universities
尤其現在大學的通識課程
Because Taiwan really does not have a kind of university
因為台灣真的講沒有一種大學
It is a truly neutral university
是真正中和型大學
I often say that it is a transfer to a neutral university
我常常說是轉中和型大學
For example, National Taiwan University does not have music and fine arts
譬如說台大也沒有音樂美術
Normal University has no business
師大也沒有商業
But your general education, especially the current future development
可是你通識教育尤其現在的未來的一個發展
General education courses are increasingly important
通識教育的課程是越來越重要
We often say that we will have cultural and creative industries in the future
我們常常說我們以後要有文化創意產業
right
對不對
But cultural and creative industries
可是文化創意產業
I often tell the professors in our music department
我就常常跟我們音樂系的教授講
I said every time I go to a concert
我說我每次聽音樂會
Looking forward to gas is to understand the concert
望有望氣都是懂音樂會
I said, can you help us find a solution?
我說你們能不能夠幫我們想辦法解決
People like me who don't understand music are willing to spend money
我這種不懂音樂的人也願意花錢
Come and listen to your symphony industry
來聽你的交響業
Come and listen to your pipe business, right?
來聽你的管音業 對不對
You have to find a way to create a market
你要想辦法要創造市場
Your market will expand
你的市場才會擴大
Also you have to cultivate an existing culture
同樣你要培養一個既有文化
creative industries, the industry
創意產業 這個產業的話
you must have a market then you must have a market
你一定要有市場 那你要有市場
So you have to be in the colleague transaction
所以你就必須要在同事交易裡面
Let's improve our cultural literacy, right?
讓我們的文化素養提升 對不對
In the future, the things we design will look like LV
以後我們設計的東西看得跟變LV一樣
Everyone at least we expand
大家起碼我們擴大
So we have to pay mainland cultural literacy
所以我們要交大陸文化素養
Why because it's important after we put it together
為什麼 因為它很重要 我們把它交會之後
Its market is huge, right? We don't want to wait for a professional
它的市場就很大 對不對 我們不要交等專業
But we develop our colleagues so that it knows it's literate
但是我們培養同事 讓它知道它有文化素養
it has musicality
它有音樂素養
So I often talk to some of our music department teachers and folklore
所以我常常跟我們一些音樂系老師跟民俗
Because the Music Folklore of Normal University
因為師大音樂民俗
Every time it is the first industry in the country
每次都是全國第一之業
Then every time our other students
那每次我們其他系手的學生
going to his class next to him
要去旁邊他的課
or take his class
或者要修他的課
they all season
他們都會季節
I said why is it like this?
我說為什麼要這樣子呢
I said you can't open a music app
我說你不會開一個音樂欣賞
drive more
來開多一點
let these students
讓這些學生
Everyone knows how to appreciate music
全部懂得欣賞音樂
Isn't your market bigger?
那你市場不是更大嗎
right
對不對
Are you still afraid that your major will be expected by others?
你還怕你的專業被人家期待
impossible things
不可能的事情
Because you are in the last four years
因為你是上四年嘛
They hurry up for a year or two
他們趕快上一、兩年而已
so the euphoria amplifies it
所以那個欣凶把它擴大
the market will be bigger
市場就會更大
As a result I think we are now
結果我覺得我們現在
The one watching the art exhibition
那個看畫展
not those buyers to see
不是那些買家去看
Then just know how to draw
然後就是懂畫
As far as people in the art world look at each other
就美術界的人自己互相看
look at each other
自己互相看
then the music is all
然後音樂的都是
Those who know music should listen
懂音樂的人去聽
Listen to Jay Chou for everything else
其他的都去聽周杰倫的
this feels bad
這樣感覺很糟糕
all bad
都很糟糕
Then this should be an exhibition
那這個應該要畫展
do it complementary
就互補來做
Here is a very important thing to say
那這邊有一個很重要的就是說
Teaching and learning theories throughout digital learning
整個數位學習的教學跟學習理論
and a development of strategy and evaluation
還有策略跟評鑒的一個發展
I just talked about the issue of education
我剛才講過其實教育的問題
It's been a hundred years
已經是既有百年歷史了
But it creates this problem
但是它這個問題的產生
It is all in the process of interaction between people
都是在人跟人之間的互動過程裡面
developed it
把它發展出來了
But once information technology comes in
可是資訊科技一進來之後
some of it affects education
它的一些會影響教育
Whether it's the sequelae
不管是到後遺症也好
or a change in its learning strategy
或者它的學習策略的改變也好
will have an impact
都會有影響
On this side, we need to conduct a new discussion
這一邊我們需要重新做一個探討
So this is the difficulty and here
所以這個是困難也是在這裡
So why start putting a lot of
所以為什麼現在開始把很多
brain science wait to put it in
腦科學等等把它擺進來
just to understand
就是要去了解說
With the intervention of such technology
在這樣的科技的介入底下
Is there any other theory we want to develop
有沒有什麼其他我們要發展出來的理論
This is also a difficult part
這個也是一個很難做的一個部分
How to do it from a cognitive point of view
從認知的角度怎麼來做
How to understand how its brain changes
怎麼了解它腦筋是怎麼變化的
There is a process, how does the process work
有個歷程 歷程是怎麼做的
So this place is worth exploring
所以這個地方都是是值得來探討的
What about his sequelae, what sequelae do you have?
那他的後遺症 你有哪一些後遺症
In fact, I often tell many people
其實我常常跟很多人講說
In fact, computers are really fascinating
其實電腦真的是很迷人
Whether you are a mobile phone or a tablet computer
不管你是手機也好 你是平板電腦也好
Or a personal computer, both are fascinating
或者個人電腦也好 都是非常迷人
But because he's charming, it's easy to get lost
但是因為他很迷人 所以我們很容易迷失
Because he has too many sequelae that will cause
因為他有太多後遺症會造成
But if you don't deal with it well, you will really get lost
可是沒有處理好之後 真的就迷失掉
The impact might last a lifetime
那影響搞不好是一輩子
You can do your own experiments
各位可以自己做實驗
say you are above your office
譬如說你在你的辦公室上面
next to you if you use the computer a lot
你旁邊 如果你常常用電腦的話
You use a computer next to you, so you study here
你旁邊用一部電腦 那你在這邊讀書
I assure you that you will not concentrate on reading
我跟你保證你讀書一定不專心
Because you run into your computer every 15 minutes
因為你每隔15分鐘會跑到你的電腦裡面
Check if there is an email coming in
看看有沒有email進來
See if anyone wants to chat with you on Facebook
看看有沒有人要到Facebook跟你聊天
Is that right?
是不是這樣 對不對
You're mentally retarded, right?
智障這樣子啊 對不對
That's too much insurance
那太多乾保了
but if you do well
但是你如果做得好
I teach parents a trick
我教各位父母一招
This is very important
這個很重要
my wife did it
這我太太做過了
because my son
因為我兒子
When I was from elementary school to middle school
那時候從國小到國中的時候
that summer vacation
那個暑假
One day during that summer vacation, he said
那個暑假他有一天他就說
He wants to chat with his classmates
他要跟同學去聊天
This is not bad
這個還不錯嘛
Since I just graduated, I want to chat with my classmates
因為剛畢業就想跟同學去聊天
We thought you were a good kid
我們就覺得你這個小孩子不錯
Why
為什麼
Because before full of classmates
因為滿有同學之前
it's time why don't you go out
就時間到為什麼不出去
I can't figure it out
我有想不通
It's time to come, why don't you go out and chat
時間明明到你為什麼不出去聊天
still at home
還在在家裡
Later I found out that their so-called chatting is online chatting
後來才知道他們所謂聊天是線上聊天
I said is it that serious?
我說有那麼嚴重嗎
Doesn't your classmate live next door to ours?
你的同學不是住在我們家隔壁嗎
also chat online
還要線上聊天
He chats online every day
他每天這個都要線上聊天
strangeness
奇怪
Then we chatted for a while
然後聊天了沒有多久
about two weeks later
大概兩個禮拜之後
I am very impressed
我印象很深
A girl from Hualing High School wrote a letter
一個花靈高中的女生寫信來
really write a letter
真的寫一封信來
Will being a parent be stressful?
當父母會不會緊張
A girl who just graduated from elementary school and a girl from Hualien High School wrote to him
一個國小剛畢業二有一個花蓮高中的女生寫信給他
I'm scared to death
我這嚇都嚇死了
But that person is small
不過那個人很小嘛
So use half of it to read his letter
所以用一半就要看他的信
I always let us think about it halfway and I see his letter
我總是讓我們想到半我就看到他的信
Fortunately, there is no problem
還好沒有什麼問題
I am more at ease
我比較安心
but how many parents do things
但是有多少父母做什麼事情
because of this
因為有這個事情
so i won't let you go online
所以我就不讓你上網
blocked you
把你擋住了
right
對不對
I want to block more seriously sometimes
我要有時候擋住更嚴重
because where will he go
因為他會跑去哪裡
he went to internet cafe
他就跑去網咖
Internet cafes were very popular back then, right?
那時候網咖很流行對不對
that's not more serious
那不是更嚴重
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
There are several strategies to do
有幾個策略要做
First
第一個
if the child was young
如果小孩子還小的時候
You put all your computers in a shared place
你把電腦全部放在共用的地方
in the study
放在書房
If he surfs the Internet for a long time, you walk around next to him
如果他上網很久你就在旁邊走來走去
Make him uncomfortable online
讓他上網都不自在
my first
我這第一個
The second is because Yahoo didn’t need money back then.
第二個因為那時候雅虎都不用錢嘛
so my wife because my wife is a fast typer
所以我太太因為我太太打字很快
He went online to apply for an account
他就上網去申請一個帳號
then he does role play
然後他做角色扮演
He chatted with my son online
他上網跟我兒子聊天
Then half a year is his
然後半年是他的
classmate's
同學的
your classmate
你同學
that's good that's really useful
那個很好 那個真的很有用
When he passed the exam, he went online to talk to him about it.
其中考到的時候 他就上網跟他講說
My mom said that's what he was going to say
我媽媽說 就是他要說的啦
My mother said because we want to take the exam
我媽媽說 因為我們要其中考
So we have to work hard, what?
所以我們要好好用功啊 什麼什麼
He didn't know until college
他一直到 大學才知道
which girl is his mother
哪一個女生是他媽媽
hehe
呵呵
So it’s really good if you do well on the Internet, right?
所以你網路做得好也真的不錯對不對
Existing tutoring function
既有輔導功能
It depends on how you use it
看你怎麼用而已
So everyone thinks that Xie Computer is also good
所以各位就覺得 協電腦也不錯
It's good to type faster
打字快一點也很好
He always has this instrument, right?
他總是有這種樂器 對不對
You can go tutor your own children
可以去輔導自己的小孩子
similar to this
類似這個
But there are so many unknowns
但這裡面有太多未知
we really need to develop
我們真的需要去開發出來
There are too many theories that are not yet known
有太多理論現在都還不知道
of course i don't know yet
我當然還不知道
So I say that this field has an advantage that is to say
所以我說這個領域有一個好處就是說
can almost redo the problem of education
幾乎可以把教育的問題重新做一遍
platform change
平台換
I usually change
我平常換的
So this is full
所以這個是滿有
In addition, the roles of teachers and agreements have changed
另外老師跟協議的角色改變
This is the most impressive
這個最有印象就是
I am a graduate student
我自己一個研究生
that graduate student
那個研究生
He once I was looking for a software
他有一次我要找一個軟體
I can't find it
我都一直找不到
He said it's okay, teacher, I'll give it to you in a few days
他說老師沒關係我過幾天就給你了
He really gave it to me in a few days
過幾天他真的就給我了
I wonder why he is so powerful
我就覺得很奇怪他怎麼那麼厲害
why so powerful
怎麼那麼厲害
he can give me something right away
他可以馬上就把東西給我
he doesn't speak
他也不講
Later it was hard
後來好不容易
Then his information ability is much better than mine
那他資訊能力比我強多了
Later he
後來他就
just graduated
就畢業了
His cooperation told me teacher you know
他的協力跟我說老師你知道
He is the stationmaster of the underground website outside
他是外面的地下網站的站長
So I actually have a student
所以我竟然有一個學生
underground webmaster
地下網站站長
You can get me various software
可以拿各種不同軟體給我
i feel weird
我是覺得很奇怪
what does this mean
那這個表示什麼意思
If we use this angle of information
如果用資訊的這個角度
I can't keep it up
我已經沒有辦法維持了
Because his IT skills are much better than mine
因為他資訊技能比我好太多了
So I say a kind of teacher
所以我說老師的一種
The role of university teachers needs to be changed
大學老師的角色要改
What you want to teach him may not be direct knowledge
你要教他的可能不是直接的知識
It's the meta knowledge
而是那個meta knowledge
may become like this
可能變成這樣
one change one big change
一個改變一個很大的改變
there is another one
那另外還有一個
He used to have an Altros at Central University
以前中央大學他有一個雅卓士
Then you can start classes on Altros
那在雅卓士上面你可以開課
Then he later transferred Altros to Chunghwa Telecom
然後他後來他把雅卓士移給中華電信
Turns out there is a very hot teacher
結果有一個很熱門的一個老師
That Besker I'm talking about is Chen Shiyuan
在講那個Besker 就是陳世遠
very popular
非常熱門
Then I found out that the teacher
然後後來才知道那個老師
Is a student of the Central China Normal University
是師大 副中 國中部的學生
do you know wes
你懂維斯嗎
So on the Internet you will feel that
所以在網路上裡面你會覺得說
You think he's great, maybe he's a teacher
你覺得他很厲害的可能是一個老師
it could be me but what
可能是我 可是呢
he can wes
他可以維斯
But in real environment
但是在現實的環境裡面
he is your student
他是你的學生
So this role is a big change
所以這個角色一個很大的一個轉變
You know a lot about the roles of teachers and students
你懂很大 就老師跟學生的角色
In particular, the role of the teacher needs to change
尤其老師的角色要改變
The role of the teacher what you are going to teach him
老師的角色 你要教他的東西
may not be transfer of knowledge
可能不是知識面的傳遞
but another aspect
而是另外一個面向
my change
我這個改變
what about the second one
那第二個呢
The way students learn also changes
學生的學習方式也改變
my way of learning
我那個學習方式
The teacher may later become a facilitator
老師可能以後變成一個引導者
He's also a no-talker
他也是一個不提者
Come up with a topic and guide
不一個題目出來 然後引導
guide
引導
one of our practices
我們的一個做法
However, the perspective of students has also changed.
可是學生角度也改變了
Now there is a kind of interactive communication
現在有一種叫交互交協華
That is to say, we have always believed that
就是說我們一直認為
If students can ask questions
學生如果會出題的話
The student's understanding of knowledge is very high
那這學生對知識的理解的程度是很高的
so often what happens
所以常常會怎麼樣
meeting
會
The student poses a question for another student to answer
這個學生出題給另外一個學生來解答
can you understand me
能不能了解我的意思
I do this often
我常常會這樣做
The teacher-student perspective has changed
這個老師跟學生的角度改變
But our traditional education is still a big problem
不過我們傳統教育還是很大的問題
You want our primary school teacher
你要我們國小老師
I think our elementary school teachers are really hardworking
我覺得我們國小老師真的很辛苦
salary is not high
薪水又不高
a lot of working hours
工作時間又很多
Why
為什麼
Change homework every time
每次改作業
raw knowledge
生智部
Do you have any impression
各位有沒有印象
If a word is wrong in the Ministry of Health and Intelligence
生智部的時候如果一個字錯的話
I have to write 30 times when I go home, right?
回家要寫30次對不對
The job of the teacher is to pick out the shortcomings of the students
老師的工作就專門在挑寫生的毛病
what's wrong where's wrong
哪裡錯了哪裡錯了
Then the job is like this
然後作業也是這樣
multiple choice
要明明選擇題
Clear choice
明明選擇題
Then that answer is C
然後那個答案是C
Choose A for sketching, right?
寫生選擇A對不對
Then sketch must write CCC 3 times next to A
然後寫生一定要在A旁邊要寫CCC3次
Is it this way
是不是這樣
Isn't it strange that we teach you to speak
我們教育你不是講很奇怪嗎
Then the calculation problem was wrong, right?
然後那個計算題計算錯了對不對
Then go back to timeout
然後回去要超時變
Write that process 10 times
把那個過程寫10次
How can this education improve
這個教育怎麼會進步
Because SASIS is still wrong
因為SASIS還是錯
We sketch the same word can be wrong
我們寫生同一個字可以錯
Maybe I'm still wrong until I'm 20
搞不好錯到20歲還在錯
why is this
為什麼會這樣
because you never gave him a chance to find fault
因為你從來沒有給他找錯誤的機會
So I often tell the teacher
所以我常常跟老師講說
The first one, your salary is not high
第一個你薪水也不高
Because I once gave a speech at an elementary school
因為我有一次到國小去演講
i was very angry
我就很生氣
I'm speaking and I speak so well
我在演講我又講得那麼好
The bottom is changing homework
底下都在改作業
you will be angry
你都會被生氣
I'm changing my homework the next day, right?
第二天都在改作業啦 對不對
ah you can blame them
啊 你就能怪他們
Thinking about it later, it's really pathetic
後來想一想 也真的很可憐
because we all asked him to
因為我們都要求他這樣做
Look at the teacher in Anqing Class
你看說安清班的老師
Anqing class teacher
安清班的老師
Is it his job only to do
是不是他的工作只有做什麼
Just change homework
改作業而已
So let our students have a habit
所以養成我們的學生有一個習慣
very bad habit
很不好的習慣
we only have one thing to do
我們只有把一件事情做完
but didn't do a thing well
但是沒有把一件事情做好
Many of our graduate students are like this
我們現在很多研究生都這樣
Right? That's why I never help students.
對不對 所以我從來不去幫學生
I helped a student revise a paper once
我有一次就幫學生改論文
I'm almost editing his composition
我幾乎在幫他改作文
I'm so angry that I'm yours after all
我就很氣好說我到底是你的
Information teacher or your Chinese teacher?
資訊老師還是到底是你的國文老師
Every time I have to help him change his composition
每次都要幫他改作文
That word, I found a typo
那個文詞啦 找錯字啦
I'm always like this
我都是這樣子
that's not right
那個都不對
So it should be reversed
所以其實應該反過來
In fact, our parents have to be patient.
其實我們家長也要有耐心啦
And teachers have to communicate with parents
而且老師要跟家長溝通
For example, find that typo
譬如說找那個錯字
why don't you look for it like this
你就不要這樣找嘛
You just ask the students to find typos
你就讓學生去找錯字
homework for students to go back on their own
作業讓學生自己回去
Just start by saying that there are two mistakes on this page
你就先說這一頁有兩個地方有錯
go back and find it, right?
回去找 對不對
Students go back and find it by themselves.
學生就回去自己去找啊
The young age on that page, will you be able to find it the first time you look for it?
那頁低的年紀 第一次找會不會找得到
Are you sure you won't find it?
保證找不到嘛
Because they never had that belief
因為他們從來沒有這種信念嘛
so he won't find
所以他會找不到
what to do if you can't find it
那找不到怎麼辦
It doesn't matter if you come back. It's always okay.
那回來沒關係 老是說好嘛
It doesn't matter if you can't find it on this page
那你這一頁找不到 沒關係
Then there is a typo in Shang Han.
那這商涵裡面有一個錯字吧
You just switch to zoom out, right?
你就把換為縮小 對不對
Go back and look for it, he will look for it from inside Shang Han
再回去找 他就從商涵裡面去找
What if you still can't find it?
那如果還找不到呢
Then there is a typo in one line, right?
那就一行裡面有錯字嘛 對不對
Is there a typo in the three words?
三個字裡面有錯字嘛
one time you'll find
總有一次你會找到
But you also develop an opportunity for him to self-diagnose
但是你也養成他自我診斷的一個機會
right, you said that math
對不對 你說那個數學
That counting error in how many students we have is a miscalculation
我們有多少學生的那個算數錯誤是計算錯誤
But what will they know later that he miscalculated
可是他們什麼之後會知道他計算錯誤
If you let them find the wrong reason every time
如果每一次讓他們找那個錯誤的理由的話
They make a typo every time because I miscalculated
他們每次打錯 因為我計算錯誤
I tell you after the current events he will
我跟你講經過時事之後他會
Will there be any more miscalculations?
會不會再計算錯誤
because he'll know he's miscalculated every time he's wrong
因為他會知道他每次錯都計算錯誤
right like this
對不對 類似這樣
The same is true for composition changes, because every time students
改作文也是一樣 因為每次學生
It’s very hard for the teacher to correct them. Of course, you can help him correct a few articles.
老師都改了也很辛苦 當然你可以幫他改幾篇
Because you have to comment, sometimes you can exchange and change the composition
因為你要評論 有時候你可以交換改作文
Let me tell you that we humans have a common problem
我跟你講 我們人類有一個通病
I can’t even find my own fault, so I’m very accurate in finding someone else’s fault
找自己的錯都找不到 找別人做特別準
Right? After you exchange and change
對不對 你交換改之後
Let me tell you he picks faults very well
我跟你講他挑毛病挑得很特別好
Right, it's ok after changing it a few times
對不對 改過幾次之後都可以
This human really needs to be cultivated but almost none of us have
這個人類真的要培養 但是我們幾乎都沒有
How can I do this kind of training with a computer?
這樣的訓練 那怎麼用電腦來做
right
對不對
The computer itself is to create an environment
電腦本身就是要建立一個環境
But this environment is always in use
可是這個環境是隨在使用
It is an environment that helps students learn
它是幫助學生學習的一個環境
Rather than expecting students to learn
而不是在期待學生學習
So one of this part
所以這個部分的一個
because how did i jump here
因為我怎麼跳到這裡來
I was just here
我剛在
Therefore, the roles of teachers and students are sometimes
所以老師跟學生的角色 有時候要
Adjust it. When I am a teacher, I often
調整一下 當老師我常常
Then the salary is not very high, each salary increase is only 3%
然後薪水沒有很高 每次加薪只有3%
as little as he does that doesn't have to work
像他那麼少,那也不必工作
Too responsible teachers sometimes create irresponsible students
太負責的老師有時候會造成不負責的學生
This, the evaluation of the effectiveness method
這個,那成效方法的評估啦
This, this at present, before Ye Lai
這個,這個目前,夜來以前都是
bright marriage salary, or straight marriage salary
亮的婚薪,或者直的婚薪
Now it's mass blending together to do
現在是質量混合在一起做
And then put brain science into it
然後還有把腦科學把它擺進來
So this kind of marriage salary model is more and more, more and more development
所以這種婚薪的模式是越來越多,發展越來越多
even through videotape
甚至可以透過錄影帶
After you shoot the videotape, then
你攝影之後錄影帶,然後
Then describe its learning status
然後把它的學習狀態描述出來
Which learning state would you jump from this learning state to?
你會從這個學習狀態跳到哪個學習狀態
Then jump from this learning state to which angle, and then evaluate
再從這個學習狀態跳到哪個角度,然後再去評估
Is there a significant difference from this state to this state?
這個狀態到這個狀態是不是有顯著的差別
I use statistics, so I will put the statistics
我用統計,所以會把統計
Integrate with that straight marriage salary
跟那個直的婚薪整合在一起
Liang and Zhi will integrate it together, so this is a more and more scientific approach
亮跟直會把它整合在一起,那這個就越來越科學化的一個做法
Okay, so this is the part about information literacy
好,那這個是有關資訊素養的部分
This has probably been mentioned just now, the first digit gap
這個剛才大概已經講過,第一個數位落差
This number is far behind Taiwan
這個數位落差台灣
So far so good, but there are some problems
目前還好,不過的確也有一些問題啦
In recent years, the situation of digital gap has indeed been
最近幾年的確把數位落差的情況
That is to say, your symbiosis in the north
就是說,你北部的協生
Is it similar to the South's symbiosis information capability?
跟南部的協生資訊能力是不是差不多
Now it's not a digital gap
現在反而不是數位落差
Now we in Taiwan don't seem to be
現在我們台灣好像不是
Like Yinyin gap, math gap
像殷隱落差啦,數學落差啦
It seems that there are all kinds of gaps
好像各種落差都有
Yes, it's getting worse
都有,越來越嚴重
The gap in that part is getting worse
就那一部分的落差越來越嚴重
this is
這個是
It has indeed improved a lot in recent years.
那最近幾年這方面的確是改善很多
Of course there is one more
當然現在還有一個是
How do you detect this gap?
這個落差你怎麼偵測
how do you define
你怎麼去定義
The so-called digital gap
所謂的數位的落差
Digital gap
數位落差
how do you detect it
那你怎麼把它偵測
And then react very quickly
然後很有快速的反應出來
On the contrary, this mechanism is not easy to do.
反而這個機制反而比較不好做
How do you define what is called drop
你怎麼去定義什麼叫做落差
Then in this gap
然後這個落差裡面
A print that can be accessed through the Internet
可以透過網路的一個印作
and react anytime
然後隨時反應出來
How much has the situation of its gap changed?
說它的落差的情形變化有多大
So this should be dealt with by the government
所以這個應該政府要去處理
Additional Internet Literacy Section
另外網路素養的部分
It has probably been said just now
剛才已經有大概有講過了
Now Internet literacy does not mean that you understand the principles of the Internet
現在網路素養不是說你懂網路的原理
For example, 70% of your network has a network protocol
譬如說你網路有七成的一個網路的 protocol
That kind of agreement is not about that
那種協定不是講那個
That's a professional doing it
那個是專業的人在做
But where is the quality of a non-professional person?
可是非專業的人他的素養在哪裡
So are we going to redefine it?
那我們是不是要重新定義出來
And now different technology comes in
然後現在不同的科技又進來了
Various technologies come in
各種不同科技進來
Is that a form of your problem solving?
那是不是你的解決問題的一個形態
will also change
也會跟著改變
like this
像類似這個
this is
這個是
That's the hardest thing to do right now
那這個是目前是最難做
I'm still working on a very interesting topic
現在還有在研究一個很有趣的題目
We call it presence
我們叫做臨場感
presence
臨場感
For example we do
譬如說我們做
Now everyone is very present, right?
現在各位都很有臨場感對不對
because we can talk to each other
因為我們是可以互相討論的
face to face
面對面的
But when on the Internet
可是在網路的時候
your teacher may be in taipei
你的老師可能在台北
Then your business students may be all over the world
那你的企業生可能在全球各地
His sense of presence is gone
他的臨場感不見了
right
對不對
What about the sense of presence?
那臨場感不見呢
Then how do you improve the sense of presence?
那你怎麼去提高臨場感
I'm in trouble now
我現在問題麻煩了
what is presence
那什麼叫臨場感
how do you define presence
你怎麼定義臨場感
So a group of teachers are studying this
所以有一批老師在研究這個
specializing in how
專門在研究怎麼
Improving the sense of presence in the Internet age
在網路時代裡面把臨場感把它提升
Now I know like geoprotocol
現在我知道像地理協議
sense of place
有叫做地方感
I just recently developed a sense of place
我最近才協到一個地方感
For example, if I go to Tamsui
譬如說我到淡水
after freshwater
那到淡水之後
what methods can i use to improve my sense of place in freshwater
我用什麼方法可以提高我對淡水的地方感
As far as I agree with Tamsui
就我認同淡水
then what about me
然後我怎麼樣怎麼樣
It has a definition out
它有一個定義出來
I am very abstract
我這個都很抽象的東西
start slowly materializing it
開始要慢慢把它實物化
slowly quantify it
慢慢把它量化
So this whole process
所以這種整個歷程
The history I use is also currently in
我使用的歷程也都目前都在
A discussion like this
類似這樣的一個探討
So when I used to be on the Internet
所以把以前在網路時
Problems that would not exist in the non-Internet era
在非網路時代不會有的問題
However, in the era of Internet in mainland China, there will be
可是大陸網路時代就會有
The topic of this study arises
這種研究的題目就出現了
How can we discuss the sense of presence in education like before?
像以前怎麼會去探討教育的臨場感
No, because it's all natural
不會啊 因為都很自然
want to be together
要都在一起啊
But in the Internet age
可是網路時代裡面
Presence becomes very important
臨場感就變得很重要啦
We want to improve our sense of presence
我們要提升我們的臨場感
right
對不對
that...that...
那...那...
Well...motivation is also important
那...學習動機也很重要
for example
譬如說
how do i... how do i increase your motivation to study
我怎麼...我怎麼提高你的學習動機
The learning motivation is only
那學習動機只有
What is the motivation for learning for the first time?
第一次使用的學習動機呢
Still need magnetism for learning motivation
還是要磁器的學習動機
right
對不對
How to improve it
那這個怎麼把它提高
i through the internet
我透過網路
how can i raise it
我怎麼來把它提高
Because your individual study is very lonely
因為你個人學習是很孤單的
because in the classroom
因為在教室裡面
you have companions
你還有同伴
but when online
但是在網路的時候
you are learning alone
你是個人在學習
you are doing it yourself
你自己在做
that's what you're doing
那自己在做
How do you improve his learning motivation
你怎麼提高他的學習動機
And this motive needs a magnet
而且這個動機還要磁器
right
對不對
so something like this one
所以類似這一個
this question
這一個問題
to discuss
都要去探討
a part of him
他的一個...一個部分
Of course, there are generally two motivations for learning.
那當然學習動機一般有兩種
class motivation
一個叫做類部動機
One is extrinsic motivation
一個叫外在動機啦
a class in an external
一個類在 一個外在
that generally speaking
那一般而言
small child
業小的小孩子齁
Usually you need extrinsic motivation.
通常都需要給外在動機啦
So we also encourage the power system
所以我們也鼓勵講力制度啦
must reconsider
必須要再考
If there is progress, then you will give it to him
有進步的話 那你就給他
give him a little gift
給他一個小禮物啊
This is outside winter
這個是外在冬季
We grown-ups too, why are you investing in stocks?
我們大人也是啊 為什麼你要去投資股票
Because there is winter outside, because you will make money
因為有外在冬季嘛 因為你會賺錢嘛
Right, but when you often lose money
對不對 可是你常常虧本的時候
So what to do, you have to study how to make money
那怎麼辦 你只好去研究怎麼賺錢嘛
so you might look into that
所以你可能會研究那個
What technical analysis of what stock?
什麼股票的一個什麼技術分析啊
But you may study to a certain stage
可是你可能研究到一個階段之後
you think he's funny
你覺得他很有趣啊
Right? Not only can he help you make money, but he
對不對 他不但可以幫你賺錢 而且他
there is his smell
有他的氣味在啊
Then change from external winter to internal winter
那就由外在冬季轉成內在冬季來
Because you think it's interesting and you're willing to take over again
因為你覺得很有趣 你願意再去接手
So we are often motivated from the outside
所以我們常常動機是從外在
then switch to the inner
然後轉換到內在
So the initial motivation
所以一開始的動機
computerized a motive
電腦化了一個動機
computer games or computer
就電腦遊戲或者電腦
computer washing part
電腦行洗的部分
just arouse your motivation first
就先引起你的動機
To arouse you through the external winter
透過外在冬季去引起你
But slowly it will return to the inner winter
但是慢慢的要歸到內在冬季
otherwise he won't last
不然他不會持久
won't last like this whole research journey
不會持久 像這個整個研究的歷程
Another very important
另外還有一個很重要
Now
現在
in the internet age
在網路時代裡面
A very important one is the sequelae of the Internet
一個很重要的就是網路的後遺症
My sequelae are really big
我這個後遺症的確是很大
What is the sequelae?
那到底有哪一隻後遺症
There's really something we don't know yet
真的有一些我們還不明了
Then we still have to explore
那還是要去探
Now I only know that there are many people sitting in Internet cafes
現在只知道有很多人坐在網咖
After sitting for a long time, the result is a stroke
坐了久了之後結果會腦中風
I'm all sequelae
我這個都是後遺症
Then I just said that when you were next to a computer
那剛才我講了你一個電腦旁邊的時候
you sit on this side he will interfere with you
你坐在這一邊他會干擾你
right
對不對
I have a lot of sequelae like this
我很多類似這個後遺症
Is there any age difference
那有沒有年齡的差別
For example, say you have reached a certain grade
譬如說你到了某一個年級
after age
年齡之後
These side effects are gone
這些後遺症就不見了
disappear without form
就無形就不見了
But you are below high school
可是你在高中以下
you like on facebook
你喜歡上Facebook
Like many adults don't like to go to Facebook these days
像現在很多大人也不喜歡上Facebook
right
對不對
because feel
因為覺得
There's no point in chatting with him online.
上網跟他聊天也沒什麼意義
But kids love it
可是小孩子就很喜歡
right
對不對
So is there an effect of age?
所以是不是會有年齡的影響
I have a discussion topic like this
我類似這樣的一個探討的議題
I'm worth it
我這個都是值得來
to study
來 study
I specifically bring this up as
我特別把這個提出來是
Because of
是因為
So we want to be able to
所以我們希望能夠
And this can indeed improve
而且這個的確可以提高
motive for action
行動機
Increase ability to act
提高可以行動機
So how should you design
所以你應該怎麼設計
But gamification software
但是遊戲化軟體
If saving the game itself
如果存遊戲本身
it also has side effects
它也有後遺症
So this is a very difficult design
所以這個是一個非常難設計的
so we call it
所以我們把它稱為
serious game
serious game
serious is a very serious game
serious就一個很嚴肅的遊戲
then you have a solution
那你就有解決
This is a contradiction, the game can still be very serious
這個是矛盾啦,遊戲還可以很嚴肅的
But the application of education is to be like this
可是教育的應用就是要這樣
So this is a very complex
所以這個是一個很複雜的
a part, a development of a very complex part
一個部分,很複雜的部分的一個發展
Of course this is too
那當然這個也是
worth exploring, because in fact
值得去探討,因為事實上
it exists
它是存在
There is also this phenomenon
也存在這個現象
So how do we put the game part
那我們怎麼把遊戲的部分
import it into learning
把它導入到學習上面
more normal use
更正常的使用
So there's a lot of the same
所以這裡面有很多一樣
its content design , its theory
它內容的設計,它的理論
and evaluation of its strategy
還有它的策略的評量
even its man-machine interface
甚至它的人機界面
This tool needs to be discussed and developed
這個工具,都有需要來做一個討論跟發展
It's a really difficult part
也的確是很困難的一個部分
Let's take a look at the part that is currently under development.
那我們看看前面所講的都是現在正在發展的部分
i need to do it again
我都需要再做的
What are the possible future scenarios?
那未來可能的情境是什麼
my first
我第一個
your future classroom
你的未來教室
future school etc.
未來學校等等
future learning style
未來學習方式
even future teachers
甚至未來的老師
I recently talked to our
我最近就跟我們那個
Our physical education teacher said
我們那個體育系的老師講
I said we have so many players
我說我們有那麼多選手
right
對不對
So many players often compete outside
那麼多選手也常常在外面比賽
Then how do we provide a good teaching model
那我們怎麼提供一個很好的教學模式
instead of saying
而不是說
Only for class or what kind of use
只有用上課啊或用什麼樣啊
Are there different ways of teaching
有沒有不同的教學方式
Let these players learn more
讓這些選手學的更多
then his
然後他的
his grades are better
他的成績更好
And he's more employable in the future
而且他未來的就業能力更強
Instead of saying that I have three marriages
而不是說我三個協婚
how many hours are you coming
你要來幾個小時
But he is often not there
可是他常常不在啊
what to do
怎麼辦
so something like this
所以類似這樣
There seems to be an experimental one abroad in the UK
在國外在英國好像有一個實驗的一個
one
一個
For example, he said that when you go to a certain department
他就譬如說你到某一個系
Then he set up to say
然後他就設定說
Okay, you've only had to solve 20 problems for four years
好 你四年來 你只要解解20個問題
After you solve all the problems, you will graduate
你問題全部解完之後就給你畢業了
But every question he asks is to cross fields
可是他每一個問題就是要跨領域
You have to read a lot of books to understand
你要讀很多本書來解解
problem-oriented planetary model
就以問題為導向的行星模式
I also have such a practice
我也有這樣的一個做法
From now on, there will be more media and more tools
那現在以後媒體更多 工具越多
The change of the form of your evil image
那你的邪象的形態的改變
Now there is another terrible
現在還有一個很可怕的
I don't know when
這個不知道什麼時候
Also, the development of digital TV in Taiwan is relatively slow
還有台灣數位電視發展比較慢
After that, the digitalized machine price environment will be slanted
那以後數位化的機價斜斜環境
because digital tv
因為數位電視
A digital TV is a computer from a certain point of view
數位電視就是從某個角度就是一部電腦
So many of your interactive teaching desks can be placed on it
所以你很多互動的教臺就可以放在上面
so i hope he doesn't arrive so early
所以我是希望他不要那麼早到
Because I prefer to enjoy life
因為我是比較喜歡享受生活
I'm sitting in the living room and I still have to study with you, right?
我坐在客廳還要跟你學習 對不對
I might as well go to a acting show, right?
我還不如去看部代戲 對不對
But this is weird
可是這個很奇怪啊
But there may be such a problem in the future
可是以後可能會有這種問題啊
So will this have side effects?
所以這個會不會有後遺症
you digital tv
你數位電視來
Then you have interactivity again
然後你就互動性又來了
Digital teaching materials come again
數位教材又來
digital teaching material
而且還可顯著性的數位教材
right
對不對
And he can interact with you
而且他還可以跟你互動
and integrated with the phone system
而且跟電話系統整合在一起
right
對不對
see half broken
看到一半打科碎
There is another call in
還有一個Call in進來
tell you not to sleep
叫你不要睡覺
what to do
那怎麼辦
right
對不對
so troublesome
所以很麻煩
The aftermath of this
這個以後的後遺症
very scary
很可怕
right
對不對
So Taiwan's digital TV didn't come so early
所以還有台灣的數位電視沒那麼早來
otherwise it will be miserable
不然就慘了
Will this affect
那這個會不會影響
Will
一定會
From the point of view of the assisting community
那以協助界的角度來講
inevitable problem
必然發生的問題
we need to discuss
我們就需要去探討
hopefully we'll find out
希望我們要找出
normal learning style
比較正常的學習模式
right
對不對
reduce its sequelae
把它後遺症降低
So a situation like this
所以類似這樣子的一個情況
It will be a very troublesome thing in the future
以後也是一個很麻煩的一件事情
there is another
另外還有一個
electronic learning machine
電子化的學習機
or digital toys
或者數位玩具
Another smart online learning tool
另外智慧型的網路學習工具
Join the iPad
加入iPad
EPad
EPad
This is an information feed
這個都是一個信息供給
if you design
如果你設計好的話
he really is a message
他真的是一個信息
It's like I'm talking about your iPad in the future
就好像我講以後你的iPad
As soon as the relevant information is posted here, it will come out.
這邊一照相關的信息就跑出來
He will deal with you
他就會跟你做一個處理
it's all possible
這都是可能的
Because this technology also exists
因為這個技術也是存在
right
對不對
That Pedro you must face now
那Pedro你現在必須面臨
we did something recently
我們最近就做了一件事情
all our supervisors all
我們所有的主管全部
All can't bury the iPad
全部都埋不iPad
so they are happy
所以他們都很高興哦
You see, the principal is good.
你看校長不錯啊
Give us one iPad per person
給我們一台一人一台iPad
Then I gave him a reason and said
那我那時候給他理由說
no way
沒辦法吧
Because the principal is presbyopic
因為校長老花眼嘛
So I bought an iPad after all to amplify it
所以我畢竟買一台iPad把它放大
Otherwise, can't you see it every time you look at the paper?
不然每次都看紙張看不到嘛
they thought this
他們以為這個
Actually where is my male model
其實我的陽模在哪裡
Because someone has an iPad since then
因為從此之後有人有iPad
I don't spend paper anymore
我就不再花紙本
All paper, all endless
全部紙張化全部無止化
Only then did they know that my purpose is to promote endless
他們才知道我的目的是要推動無止化
So while there's an iPad on it that can zoom in
所以雖然上面有個iPad可以放大
so happy
所以很高興
But it works well
可是效果很好啊
I think we are always learning now
我覺得我們現在老是學習的
After giving one, everyone is looking forward to it
給了一則之後大家很期望
As a result, the first time I came to a meeting, there was no paper
結果第一次來開會就是沒有紙張
Without paper, he started looking at the computer
沒有紙張他就開始看電腦
look at the screen and so on
看螢幕等等
The meeting was also good
開會的情況也不錯
so this changes
所以這就改變
this is a tool
這個都是一個工具
Therefore, in the future, this electronic protocol tool
所以以後這種電子化的協議工具
will really come more
也真的會來越多
But what will the teacher do in the future if there are sequelae?
可是會有後遺症以後老師怎麼辦
I'm thinking everyone gets an iPad
我會在想每一個人都拿一台iPad
right
對不對
Then every protocol member is busy in class
然後上課每個協議員多事
don't even look at the teacher
都不看老師
I have a feeling after endless transformation
我就無止化之後就有一個感覺
I am the chairman and no one wants to see me
我當主席沒有人要看我
no one wants to see me
沒有人要看我
Everyone is looking at his iPad and not at me
大家都是看他的iPad都不看我了
This is also a very troublesome thing in the future
這個也是一個以後也是一個很麻煩的事情
don't know how to explain the problem
不知道怎麼解釋問題
later you see
以後你看
In the future, if each symbiotic can keep one step
以後如果每一個協生能守一步
He just looks at his iPad
他就看他的iPad
Look at his tutorial tools
看他的協習工具
I see his tutorial tool
我看他的協習工具
Then the teacher interacts with the students
那這個老師跟學生互動
How to link this mechanism again
這個機制怎麼再連結
how to connect again
怎麼再連結
So this needs to be dealt with
所以這個都有需要再去處理
one of the satellites
衛星的一個
an online learning tool
一種網路學習工具
like that quiz
像那個測驗
right
對不對
Our school has developed several testing systems
我們學校有發展幾個測驗系統
also quite intelligent
也蠻有智慧的
In terms of language, we have developed
像以言方面我們有發展
For example, a few indicators and a few parameters
譬如說幾個指標幾個參數
This parameter can be used to judge the readability of your article
這個參數可以來判斷你這邊文章的可讀性
i have readability
我有可讀性
Then we have done a set of rewriting
那我們有做一套改作文的
that is we have a new book center
那是我們有一個新冊中心
Specially responsible for junior high school locomotives
專門負責國中機車的
original design purpose
當初設計出來的目的
See if you can expect the teacher to correct the composition
看能不能期待老師來改作文
Because it doesn't mean that the composition is graded
因為不是說作文有分級
That design is really good
那個設計出來也真的不錯
and we have evaluated
而且我們有做評估
change with real people
跟實際人去改
change with computer
跟用電腦改
how relevant is it
它的相關性有多高
Its related machine is almost the same
它的相關機幾乎是一樣
That is to say, you use a computer to change
就是說你用電腦改
follow the employer to change
跟用人去改
Actually not much difference
其實沒有差多少
In the end we dare not launch
最後我們不敢推出
Why dare not launch
為什麼不敢推出
Because no matter what you say, the parents won't believe it
因為你再怎麼說家長都不相信
that
那個
Parents don't believe it
家長都不相信
The computer can be shocked
電腦可以驚頭到啦
The idea is the same, right?
觀念是一樣的意思啊 對不對
How could his parents believe that the composition was modified by a computer?
他家長怎麼會相信說電腦改出來這個作文
It's the same as people change
跟人改的是一樣
Even if there is no so-called difference in our research
即使我們在研究上面是沒有所謂差別的
But we just dare not use that to change
可是我們就是不敢用那個去改
or use people to change
還是用人去改
Then use someone to change it
那用人去改喔
But sometimes people are wiser
不過有時候人還是比較有智慧
Like our current new car center, the remodeling is very powerful
像我們現在新車中心那個改作很厲害
So you have to believe it's fair
所以各位一定要相信它是公平的
Why
為什麼
I'll tell you a secret
我跟你們講一個幣密
All the composition teachers corrected all the essays on the computer
所有作文老師全部在電腦上面改
So all your sketches and essays
所以你所有的寫生所寫的作文
All will be scanned into the computer
全部會被scan到電腦裡面
So you look at the computers in the classroom
所以你看那個整個教室通通的電腦
All composition correction teachers sat on it and corrected
所有改作文老師就坐在上面改
Then when changing, we will hide some compositions
那改的時候我們會暗藏一些作文
Already know which set of compositions
就已經知道哪一個集分的作文
we have already classified
我們已經類定好
For example, this composition has been divided into three episodes
譬如說這一篇作文已經三集分
Then he will write this composition
然後他就會把這個作文
plug it into one of our teachers
把它插到我們一個老師身上
The teacher didn't know that this side thought it was our tears
老師不知道這邊認為是我們淚定
It's us hiding inside, not the composition of the co-existence
是我們藏在裡面,不是協生的作文
It's us, just...so that teacher will change
是我們,就...所以那個老師就會去改
Then if he changed it, he gave it a score of six
那如果改的時候,他給了六幾分
what does that mean?
那表示什麼意思?
The standard should be three points.
標準應該是三幾分啊
Then how do you give six points?
那你怎麼給六幾分?
So naturally a teacher would go to him
所以就自然有一個老師會去找他
that teacher will get him
那個老師就會把他找來
Go to a counselor for counseling
到輔導師去輔導
Just ask him what's your problem?
就問他你有什麼樣的問題啊
Then you start doing counseling
然後你什麼樣,就開始做輔導了
So as long as you are found, it means you have a problem
所以你只要被找,那就表示你有問題了
So we use something like this
所以我們用這樣子的作
So there is a counseling mechanism put in
所以有把輔導的機制擺進去
Of course, education and training must be done before changing the composition
當然要改作文以前都要做教育訓練
tell everything
全部都要講
But in education and training, we still have to be afraid of many human factors.
可是教育訓練我們還是要怕很多人為的因素啊
So we will insert some composition into it
所以我們會插了幾分作文進去
Then ask him to correct the composition
然後讓他去改這個作文
After asking him to change it, if the deviation is too large
讓他改了之後,如果偏差太大的話
we start tutoring
我們就開始做輔導
So something like this, this even the test has to come to us
所以類似這樣,這個連考試驗都要來找我們
use our trick
要用我們這一招
He also needs to change the exam, right?
考試驗他也要改嘛對不對
this is called
這個叫
So we all have faith in our counselors
所以我們對輔導人員都要信念
Everything can only be changed after belief
全部都要信念完之後才能改
The smart eLearning process
那智慧型的網路學習工藝
A four-star teaching
四星化的一種教學
I can follow your ability
我可以按照你的能力
To judge your ability and give you different teaching materials
來判斷你的能力給你不同的教材
I give you different teaching materials
我給你不同的教材
Now the four-star test is very important
現在四星化的測驗一個很重要
It is to give you different tests according to your ability
是按照你的能力來給你不同的測驗
So the quiz questions are different for each of you
所以你每一個人的測驗題目都不一樣
Give points based on your quiz questions
按照你的測驗題目來給分數
So he has such a practice
所以他有這樣的一個做法
that this
那這個
this can never be done
這個永遠做不完
because this is too much
因為這個太多了
too much worth doing
太多值得做了
Another one is that
另外還有一個是那個
this should be next
這個應該是下一個
The whole small screen learning content
那整個小螢幕的學習內容
when the screen was small
螢幕小的時候
picture
像
if you are a tablet
如果你是平板電腦
still slightly larger
還稍微比較大
If your phone is smaller
如果你是手機更小
right
對不對
A design of the whole learning content
這個整個學習內容的一個設計
There are also four-star digital learning content
還有四星化的數位學習內容
it will be the kind of talent
它會英才思交的這一種
Learning Content
學習內容
That gives you different content for judging your ability
那給判斷你的能力給你不同的內容
This is a very complicated part of me
我這個都是很複雜的一個部分
There are also agreements other than knowledge learning
另外還有知識學習以外的協議
Like this I have been encouraging teachers to do
像這個我都一直鼓勵老師在做
For example, how do you design a learning tool
譬如說你怎麼設計一個學習工具
To develop students' communication skills
來培養學生的溝通能力
how do you design a learning tool
你怎麼設計一個學習工具
To develop students' ability to be business owners
來培養學生的業主能力
It's not about knowledge
就它不是用知識面的
So how do you design tools to develop students' reasoning skills?
那你怎麼設計工具來培養學生的推理能力
A practice like this
類似這樣子的一個做法
This place is really worth developing
這個地方的確是值得發展
and it's not easy to do
而且也不是很容易來做
OK good
OK 好
Then I'm probably very simple in the end
那最後我大概很簡單的
make a conclusion
做一個結論
there are several parts
有幾個部分
The first environment where handrails no longer learn
第一個 扶手不再學習的環境
more and more international attention
越來越受國際重視
Plus the future camp end
加上以後的營端
This will definitely change our education a lot.
這個一定會對我們教育做很大的改變
Especially after the 12-year state religion came in
尤其加上十二年國教進來之後
time stretched
時間一拉長
After a stretch
一拉長之後
it will change a lot
它的改變會很大
so
所以
Now the balance of that camp
現在那個營端的平衡
Platform usage is simply too high
平台使用實在是太高了
And now many students are very good at taking a small software on the silver terminal as falling
而且現在很多學生都很會把銀端上面的一種小軟體把它當落下來
Then learn directly on the screen
然後直接在螢幕上面再學習
and even while
而且甚至可以一邊
So maybe in the future we will be very similar to Japan
所以也許以後我們會跟日本可能會很像
For example, if you go to Japan to do his MRT
譬如說如果你到日本去做他的捷運戰的捷運的時候
You will see a lot of Japanese people playing with their mobile phones over there, right?
你會看到很多日本人都拿著手機在那邊玩手機對不對
We also hope that one day we in Taiwan will also look at mobile phones
我們也希望有一天我們台灣是也在看手機
But looking at the learning class cage
但是在看學習類籠
In this way, our competitiveness is higher than his
這樣我們的競爭力就比他高了
He watched maybe a game and we watched learning cages
他看了可能是遊戲我們看的是學習類籠
maybe there will be
可能會有啊
unit becomes small
單元就變得很小
For example, your study time becomes shorter
譬如說你的學習時間變短
there are a lot of shortening
有很多變短
But the aftereffects of the place I just talked about
但這個地方我剛才講的後遺症
Knowledge will be very spilled
知識就會非常的淋散
The second high-quality learning environment
第二個優質化的學習環境
Not limited to online learning
不只限於網路學習
for dust learning
為了粉塵式學習
in the school system
在學校的系統裡面
transmission of knowledge
我們必須承認有的知識的傳遞
The transmission effect between people is better
是人跟人之間的傳遞效果是比較好的
through computer
透過電腦
It doesn't deliver that well
它傳遞效果並不會那麼理想
Then how do you teach the entity
那你怎麼把實體的教學
Integrate it with online teaching
跟網路化的教學把它整合在一起
put it together
把它整合在一起
one like this
類似這樣子的一個
For example, in your laboratory you do experiments
譬如說你實驗室你做實驗
do experiments
做實驗
on the internet
網路上面
Networked labs have their advantages
網路的實驗室有它的優點
what's the advantage
什麼優點呢
because it is simulated
因為它是模擬
simulate a laboratory
模擬一個實驗室
Simulating a lab has one benefit
模擬一個實驗室有一個好處
what it can do
它可以做到什麼習
from failure
從失敗中
write in error
錯誤中寫寫
Trial and error is not written in doing
嘗試錯誤不是做中寫
We put a lot of emphasis on writing in Chinese
我們很強調做中寫
But what?
可是呢
If it is on the Internet, it can be wrongly written
如果網路上的話可以錯中寫
you keep on trial and error
你不斷的嘗試錯誤
I try and make mistakes because it's safe
我嘗試錯誤因為很安全
it can be safe from mistakes
它可以安全的錯誤
i remember
我記得以前
I bought one of those before
以前我就買了一台那個
That Microsoft designed a Flightshake
那個Microsoft設計了一個Flightshake
Just simulate waving, right?
就模擬揮行的 對不對
I've never been trained to swing
我也從來沒有受過揮行的訓練
then play that one
那就玩那一個
Every time halfway through the game, the plane is like this
每一次玩到一半 那飛機就這樣
just come down
就下來
But no matter how much I fall, it won't affect me
可是再怎麼摔我都不影響
right or wrong
對不對 都不影響
because it is safe to experiment with
因為它可以安全的實驗
This is a very good market pattern
這個是一個很好的一個行情模式
There is indeed such a function on the Internet
那網路上的確有這個功能
I do have a lot we can't do in practice
我的確有很多我們在實際場合做不到
For example, if you do a chemistry experiment
譬如說你做化學實驗
Can you fail safely in a lab?
你難道能夠在實驗室做安全的失敗嗎
maybe come back once
可能一次就回來
But the network can continue to repeat
可是網路可以不斷地repeat
you find the best
你找到最好
And the second network also has a
而且第二個網路還有一個
One advantage of online teaching materials
網路化的教材有一個好處
able to control
可以控制
You can control the progress of teaching
你可以控制教學的進度
Can control parameter changes
可以控制參數的改變
You can go to a parameter for a Spring-style change
你可以去一個參數一個春式的改變
and watch it change
然後看它的變化
I can do it all
我這都可以做得到
There is also a section on humanities
另外還有一個有關人文的部分
The humanities part is not easy to present on the Internet
人文的部分在網路的部分比較不好呈現
this is the truth
這個是事實
Natural science is better presented
自然科學比較好呈現
But the humanities part should present really good teaching content through the Internet
但是人文的部分要透過網路呈現出真正好的教學內容
sometimes bad presentation
有時候不好呈現
Sometimes a face-to-face learning between people is better
有時候是人跟人之間的一種面對面的學習會更好
So the factor that emphasizes the so-called powder layer practice is here
所以現在很強調所謂的粉層式的行習的因素就在這裡
That is to say, there are some things that you can learn through the Internet
就是說有一些你可以透過網路化做學習
If there are some units, you study in the classroom
那有一些單元的你就在教室裡面學習
or study in the lab
或者在實驗室裡面學習
so this place is one of its focal points
所以這個地方是它的一個重點
Another tutorial that is increasingly emphasizing social groups and motivation
另外一個越來越重視群系跟動機的輔導
because of online learning
因為網路化學習
Cooperative Learning
美其名是合作學習
But the place where you study is you alone
但是你所學習的場所就是你一個
Well, there is also the aftermath of this on the Internet.
那這個還有網路上的後遺症
This is all to be dealt with
這個都是要去處理的
In addition, learning tools will become more and more simple
另外學習工具會越來越簡單
will become easier
會越來越簡單
Especially after silverization
尤其銀端化之後
Silverized complex placed on the silver side
銀端化複雜的放在銀端
right
對不對
Simple as a tablet for your personal use
簡單的像平板電腦就你個人的使用
So the computer is no longer as complicated as a normal personal computer
所以電腦已經不會像一般的個人電腦那麼複雜
It's about how to make a connection between these places
而是這個地方之間怎麼來做一個聯繫
Therefore, there are a lot of things that need to be gradually stored in the reprinted computer.
所以有很多東西就慢慢要不一定在複打的電腦裡面
Especially Taiwan's IC chip design is very powerful
尤其台灣的IC晶片設計又很厲害
As long as you can imagine it is designed for you
只要你想得到它都把你設計出來
So the tool itself can be hardened
所以這個工具本身可以硬體化
Learning tools can be hardened in the future
學習工具以後可以硬體化
In addition, there are formal learning
另外還有揮正式學習的
There are more and more opportunities for Informal learning
Informal learning的機會越來越多了
The need for education is increasing
教育需求越來越多了
So if you have a look at Luohu Tools
所以如果你有到羅湖工具看的話
You can often see many students sitting in a certain portrait
常常可以看到很多學生坐在某一個畫像裡面
then draw
然後再畫
So they've been trained like this since they were little
所以他們從小就這樣來訓練
This is all formal learning
這個都是揮正式學習
In addition, the simulation type and the game type
另外模擬式的跟遊戲系的
You can also do humanities subjects like simulation
像模擬式的也可以做到人文科目
Humanities can also be simulated
人文方面也可以做模擬
Not that only physical chemistry
不是說只有物理化學這樣
because you can simulate situations
因為你可以模擬情境
Can do situational simulation
可以做情境模擬
There is a way of learning called
有一種學習方式叫做
the kind called
那種叫做
writing with situational awareness
有情境認知的寫寫
what does it mean
它是什麼意思呢
Let's say we're driving
譬如說我們開車好了
We must drive to the coach field
我們開車一定到教練場去開
After the coaching field exam
教練場開考完之後
you have a driver's license
你有駕照
but where is the problem
但是問題在哪裡呢
Does having a driver's license mean you can drive?
你有駕照是不是代表你會開車
not necessarily
不一定啊
because you didn't practice the situation
因為你沒有做情境的練習
you go uphill
你上坡
then start uphill
然後上坡起步
And the condition of various roads
而且各種道路的狀況
you haven't practiced
你都沒有練習到
this is
這個就是
Cut and sweep the cognitive writing of that situation
切掃那個情境的認知的寫寫
there is another one like this
還有一個就是這樣
I remember
我記得
I remember exercising
我記得以前要運動
then golf
然後打高爾夫球
I don't know how to fight
我不太會打
So I go to the driving range every time
所以我每次都到練習場去打
When it comes to the driving range
那到練習場打的時候
I actually played well
我其實都打得不錯
Easy to play every time
每次都可以打得很簡單
Then I went to Australia once
那有一次到澳洲去
Then my friend said let's continue to play the scene
然後朋友說那我們繼續去打現場
it's my first time
我是第一次的
It's really embarrassing the first time
就真的第一次就很丟臉
Why
為什麼
'Cause I can't even hit the first ball
因為我連第一球都開不出去
a lot of people lined up behind
後面排了很多人
What's Next to Receive Situational Awareness
接著什麼去接到情境認知
That is to say, you did not go to that situation to write
就是說你沒有到那個情境去寫寫
So you don't even know what date you want to work at this time
所以你根本不知道說這個時候你要幾號乾啊
you don't even know
你都不知道
So this is also a
所以這個也是一個
Sometimes it can be shaped like this in a simulated environment
有時候在模擬環境裡面可以塑造成這樣
let you experience
讓你去體驗
Opportunities to write interest other than knowledge
那中視知識以外的寫息機會
I think this has just been said
我想這個剛才已經講過了
This category is a case like this
這一類是這樣子的一個情況
I'm probably talking about this very briefly
我大概很簡單的就談到這裡
Then there's a little time for you guys to ask questions.
那有一點時間給各位來問問問題
we make an interaction
我們做一個互動
make an interaction
做一個互動
Do you have
有沒有
All questions please
各方面問題來請
It is very simple to ask Principal Zhang three questions
請教張校長三個問題都很簡單
The first question is the APP software of your rigid body
第一個問題是你剛體的APP軟體
That is to say, in the future, the camp software will pass through this.
就是說以後那個營端軟體會透過這個可不可以
please explain his
請說明一下他的那個
his usefulness
他的那個用處
but the second is you
但第二個是你
Did Principal Zhang think that the Three Kingdoms game
是不是張校長認為那個三國志的遊戲
computer games for kids
電腦遊戲給小朋友玩
Parents can rest assured
家長可以很放心的
the third is
第三個是
In addition to storage
營端除了儲存之外
Ask Principal Zhang if he has other functions
請教張校長他還有沒有別的功能
Thanks
謝謝
I think the future development of the camp is really a lot
我想營端未來的發展真的是很多
because he has a lot of small supplies
因為他有很多小供給
For example, his sister has a problem in your life
譬如說他姊姊你生活上的一個問題
And he sells them very cheaply
而且他賣的都很便宜
say 0.99
譬如說0.99
$0.99 and more
0.99美元等等
then look now
那你看現在
There are many functions now
現在的功能非常多
I don't know what function it has for commuting.
那通勤我就不知道他有什麼功能
no no no
不會不會
There are a lot of software in his APP Store
他APP Store裡面就有很多軟體
Then in your APP Store
那你APP Store裡面
There are various application agents
有各種不同的應用功劑
So as long as you want all kinds of application agents
所以只要你想得到的各種應用功劑
It can be converted into an APP in the camp
都可以轉成在營端裡面的APP
So he has a great range
所以他範圍很大
So in fact our generation
所以事實上我們這一代
must face that problem
都一定會面臨那個問題
Everyone must go to understand the camp
都一定要去瞭解營端
Sometimes we ask ourselves children are faster
有時候我們問我們自己小孩子更快
Because kids are great
因為小孩子他們都很厲害
Because they have a high chance of cooperative learning
因為他們合作學習機會太高
They can exchange experiences with each other
他們可以相互經驗交流
So sometimes ask him
所以有時候去問他說
what kind of software do you want
那你要什麼樣的軟體
If you ask him, he can find it for you.
你問他他都可以幫你找得到
You can also read newspapers, magazines
你也可以讀報紙啊 讀雜誌啊
now have
現在都有
How are we now, Master Shi?
我們現在施大師怎麼樣
is lent the tablet to the students
是把平板電腦借給學生的
We're here to borrow a book, not a book
我們來借書 不是借一本書
is a tablet for you
是一部平板電腦給你
Then there are a lot of e-books in this tablet
那這部平板電腦裡面有好多電子書
We also caused him to lend him
我們也引起他借給他
You pay it back in about two weeks
你大概兩個禮拜拿來還
So the qualitative change of the library will also change in the future
所以以後圖書館的質變也會改變
He's not borrowing a book, he's borrowing a vehicle
他不是借一本書 而是借一個載具
In fact, I read e-books like this
其實看電子書 我類似這樣
So this will have many functions in the future
所以這個以後功能很多
Not only educational function
不只只有教育功能
I am not only educational
我不只教育功能
As for gamification software
那至於遊戲化軟體
really pick carefully
真的要很小心去挑
In fact, I can only see now
其實我看到現在就只有看到
a long time ago
很早很早以前的一個時代
because he cosplays
因為他做角色扮演
A lot of fun
很好玩
but he's cosplaying
但是他在角色扮演
Is there a transfer learning effect?
是不是有傳遞學習的效果
I don't think he has the knowledge to pass on
我並不認為他有傳遞知識面
but he has
但是他有
The main thing I gave that example is
我舉那個例子最主要是
He has changed your values
他有改變你的價值觀
this is one of his
這個是他的一個
This value change is sometimes impossible in transactions.
這價值觀的改變有時候是交易裡面是做不到
So it is also very difficult
所以也是很困難的一件事
but i don't encourage
但是我並不鼓勵
The kind that really let children play too much game
真的去讓小孩子玩太多遊戲化的那種
that software
那種軟體
Because our current game software is very violent
因為我們目前遊戲軟體都很暴力
Yes, so I asked Principal Zhang for advice.
對 所以我就請教張校長說
Is that the Romance of the Three Kingdoms game for children to give up?
那是不是三國志遊戲給小朋友可以放棄
Now that was ten years ago
現在那是十年前以前的
probably gone now
現在可能沒有了
it's gone now
現在沒有了
so you still have to see
所以你還要去看
what's the best now
那現在最好的是什麼
best now
現在最好
at least i personally think
我起碼我個人覺得
I don't see anything I like so far
我目前沒有看到我喜歡的
Even though it's billed as educational software
即使它號稱為教育類的軟體
But I think its educational model is wrong
但是我覺得它的教育模式是不對的
For example, there is a software that writes English
譬如說有一個軟體是寫英文
English teaching
英文教學
That English is called designing a screen
那英文叫做設計一個畫面
I design a picture
我設計一個畫面
After designing a screen
那設計一個畫面之後
There are many screens such as
畫面有很多譬如說
Just make a seawater anomaly
就做一個海水異常
Then the children can
然後小孩子呢就可以
seawater anomaly project
海水異常一計畫
you can click it and it will be given to you
你可以點一下它就點給你
Then click on each word to practice calligraphy for you
然後點每一個字就練字給你聽
But the problem is that kids won't order that.
但是問題小孩子不會去點那個啊
He can point to seawater anomalies such as parasols
他會點海水異常譬如說洋傘
He ordered a parasol parasol and it became a what
他點一個洋傘洋傘就變成一個什麼
turn into a rocket and swing out
變成一個火箭揮出去
do you know what i mean
你懂我意思嗎
At that point, the animation of a certain object will come out.
那點某一個物件物件動畫就出來
I think this
那我覺得這個喔
It was selling well
當初銷售很好啊
But in terms of our education, that is useless
可是以我們學教育來講那個沒有用
why is it useless
為什麼沒有用呢
Because the students don't know how to click the English skill
因為學生不會去點那個英文技
he's already going to something
他已經會去點什麼
click on those objects
點那些物件
Watch the animation behind them
看他們背後的動畫
so i said i think about it later
所以我說我後來想想
Barely say he is useful, say he is more humorous
勉強說他有用說他比較幽默
Because the production of his objects is beyond our imagination
因為他物件的產生超出我們想像
You said learning English is really useless
你說學英文真的也沒什麼效果
So sometimes from an educational point of view
所以有時候用教育的觀點來看
educational software
教育性的軟體
won't be very useful
並不會很有用
There are a lot of educational software that I think is wrong
有很多的教育軟體我認為是不對的
is not right
是不對
Also his animation is wrong
而且他的動畫的呈現也是錯的
For example, many of his gamified educational software
譬如說他很多遊戲化的教育軟體
an apple falls
一個蘋果掉下來
two apples fell
兩個蘋果掉了
ask you how many apples
問你幾個蘋果
make me plan is game
讓我打算是遊戲
The first one is less fun
第一個比較不好玩
That's a multimedia quiz, you know what I mean?
那是多媒體測驗 你懂我意思嗎
so be careful
所以要很小心
So why is there such research on the market saying
所以市面上為什麼要有這個研究說
We want to import formal
我們希望導入正規
Instead of letting manufacturers use it directly
而不是讓廠商用它很直接的
Designing this software from the perspective of no cognitive theory
那種沒有認知理論的角度去設計這個軟體
The most important thing is such a situation
最主要是這樣的一個情況
So that needs to be tuned and done carefully
所以那個要調 而且要小心做
not quite right
不盡然是對
In fact, this assistance community should be able to do it.
其實這個協助界應該可以做啦
but if do
但是如果做的話
Make a comment on each game software
對每個遊戲軟體做一個評論的話
we may be thrown eggs
我們可能會被丟雞蛋
It's more troublesome at this point
這比較麻煩的是在這一點
ok thank you professor thank you
好 謝謝教授 謝謝
ok guys no more questions
好 各位還沒其他問題
come please
來 請
please teach me
請教一下
There are more and more opportunities for modern people to use computers
就現代人使用電腦的機會越來越多
Fewer and fewer opportunities for assistance
就協助的機會越來越少
An old human like me will
像我現在這種舊人類都會
often forget what help
常常忘記什麼協助
that overemphasizes computer teaching
那過度強調電腦教學
What about new humans?
像來新人類怎麼辦
So we just said that we must know each other
所以我們剛剛說 一定認識
very important
很重要的
Some still need physical teaching
有一些還是要實體教學
so don't
所以不要
To think that the computer can expect us
要以為電腦可以期待我們
Because in many theories
因為在很多理論裡面
This part of Practice still needs to
Practice這個部分還是要
actually do it
實際去做
this is impossible
這個是沒有辦法的事情
so i just said
所以我剛才講說
computers are really fascinating
電腦真的很迷人
but it is easy to cause silverstone
但是很容易造成銀石
so why are we pushing this
所以為什麼我們在推動這種
When computerized bloodshed
電腦化交血的時候
Also pay attention to its sequelae
也要注意它後遺症
Then also pay attention to when it uses
然後也要注意它使用的時機
If you can't grasp this point
如果這一點沒有把握的住的話
yes it will affect
是會有影響
But we can't both
但是我們也不能夠都不用
you know what i mean ? because this is a period
你懂我意思嗎?因為這個是一個期式
because it will
因為它一定會
You don't want to be affected and you will be affected
你不想被影響也會被影響
This is like talking about networking
這個就好像說網路化裡面
Many textbooks are wrong
很多教材是錯的
I remember a teacher once said
我記得以前有一個老師就講說
Then this is called wrong, we all should not read this kind of textbook
那這個叫來錯我們大家都不要看這種教材
but you must have
可是你一定會有
but with a different attitude
可是用不同的心態
Then you go to the wrong place to find
那你就到錯的裡面去找
find something wrong
找一些錯在哪裡
So just use the one that
所以就使用的那一種
when and how to use
時機跟使用的方法
is important
是重要的
then this is us
那這個是我們
unless we don't
除非我們不要
Don't computerize everything
全部都不要電腦化
But as long as computerized
可是只要電腦化
This is a phenomenon that must be faced
這個就是一定會面臨的一個現象
This is
這是
it brings convenience
它帶來方便性
But it also has repercussions
可是它也帶來後遺症
There are some words we often forget too
有一些字我們也常常忘記
right
對不對
because of the enemy
因為敵界
Now the enemy has this problem
現在敵界有這個問題
So your concern is the existence of
所以你關心的問題是存在
But what we really want to care about
可是我們真的要把關心的問題
find a way to make it normal
想辦法讓它成為正常
Do you have any other questions?
各位還沒有其他問題
please
來請
Like Professor Zhang's answer just now
像剛才張教授的回答
i thought of a question
我想到一個問題
In fact, what students need most is
就是其實學生最需要的是
he has the ability to judge
他有能力去判斷
what is good quality
什麼是優質的東西
That
那
that is
就是說
Now
現在
you can know say
你可以知道說
A lot of game software is not that good
很多遊戲軟體並不是那麼好
But
可是
Like all parents, the primary concern is
就像所有的家長最關心的是
Do you still have the ability to judge
還是是有沒有判斷能力
right
對
This leads to the essence of education
這個就引申到教育的本質
In fact, we in Taiwan are really admitted
其實我們台灣真的是被聯考
Dreaming that there are many abnormal teaching
夢到有很多是不正常的教學
it's really helpless
這真的很無奈
Because this is no longer a question of so-called educational ideals
因為這個已經不是所謂的教育理想的問題
but a political issue
而是一個政治問題
As long as there are political issues, many things are unsolvable
只要碰到政治問題很多東西都無解
But it's also a question of fairness
可是它也是一個公平性的問題
Because we haven't developed
因為我們還沒有發展出來
Come out on that what communication skills
出來對那個什麼溝通能力
Its venom ability a good Pacific system
它液毒能力一個很好的平洋系統
Then as long as your school is divided into good schools and bad schools
那你學校只要有分成好學校跟不好的學校
there is this problem
就有這個問題
i have this problem
我就有這個問題
so this is
所以這個是
So we are not a normal teaching
所以我們不是一個正常教學
I want to promote in Normal University recently
我最近想要在師大裡面推動
Put that maliciousness and the three evils into effect
把那個惡意跟三惡起效
You students, don't talk nonsense
你們學生不要隨便亂講
I'm just pushing right now
我只是現在正在推動而已
Why?
為什麼?
because I always feel
因為我一直覺得
It is not easy for you to get into a school
你要考進來一個學校不容易
then why don't you give it
那你為什麼不給它
give it a little more time to study
讓它多一點時間去學習
give it some chance
給它一些機會
Especially our boys are relatively slow in academic achievement
尤其我們男生學習成就都比較慢
to show
才要表現
then you should let
那你應該讓
It's not about his character
他又不是品性上的問題
right
對不對
But we talk to many actors like me
可是我們像我也跟很多戲手講啊
You said I said people want to play tricks
你說我說人家要轉戲
like us say we shadow play
像我們譬如說我們陰影戲
Can't go home every time
每次都不能家轉進去
because he thinks he
因為他認為他
He scored very well in the entrance examination
他聯考進來成績很高
I'm only ten points away.
我也是不過差十幾分而已
right
對不對
Then what does it matter if you make him look like this?
那你給他長這樣有什麼關係
and you're not
而且你又不是
unless your resources are limited
除非說你的資源有限
Because there are so many in one class
因為一個班級就這麼多
If you transfer in, he may not be able to attend class.
如果你轉進來他可能沒辦法上課
Otherwise, do you try to let him turn?
不然你就盡量讓他轉嘛
because we have a survey
因為我們有一個調查
that's really scary
那真的很可怕
We have a program from our Normal University called
我們從我們師大有一個叫做
Higher Education Database
高等教育資料庫
So we will analyze the situation of each school
所以我們都會分析各個學校的情況
Then put the students
然後把學生
why do you write this department
為什麼你會寫這個科系
Why did you study this school
為什麼會讀這個學校
More than half are based on the opinions of parents and teachers
一半以上是聽家長跟老師的意見
really so
真的是這樣
and then after coming in
然後然後進來之後
related to his information after coming in
進來之後跟他信息有關的
In fact, a certain percentage is irrelevant
其實有一定的比例是無關的
He didn't want to read it
就他本來就不想讀的嘛
but he came in
可是他進來了
why don't you let him at the college level
你為什麼不讓他在大學階段
Go after what he wants to do
好好的去追求他想要做的
what's the matter with spending a little more time
多花一點時間有什麼關係
For example, it should be a normal four-year graduation
譬如說應該正常畢業四年
what does it matter if it takes two more years
多花兩年有什麼關係
There are many who are not graduating
現在很多讀不畢業的
Achievements higher than ours abound
成就比我們高比比皆是
right
對不對
So sometimes the idea is to change
所以有時候觀念是要改變
But this place needs time to adjust
但是這個地方要有時間去調整
For example, I always feel
譬如說我一直覺得
Twelve Zero Country is a very important part
十二零國家是一個很重要的一個部分
That is to say, if he can
就是說他如果能夠
Take this Metal Ability well
好好的把這種Metal Ability
come out with good faith
好好的信念出來
In fact, our competitiveness in the future is very strong
其實對我們未來的競爭力是很強的
Look at how much we learn how to communicate.
你看我們多少學能溝通能力不行
Powerpoint won't do either
Powerpoint也不會做
Knowledge collation will not write that report
知識整理也不會寫那個報告
it's bad too, isn't it?
也是很糟對不對
It's all about faith
這個都要信念的
have faith
都要信念的
so this is your question
所以這個是你講的問題
is a big environmental problem
是一個大環境的問題
We can't even do our own mistakes
我們連自己哪裡錯都不會了
How to judge whether this thing is good or bad
怎麼去判斷這個東西好壞
right
對不對
In fact, the whole paragraph can't come out.
其實整段都整段不出來
how do you judge
你怎麼去判斷
Because we can't blame the kids
因為我們這不能怪小孩子
we didn't give him a chance
我們沒有給他機會
In addition, I think the next generation
另外我覺得下一代
like i have many assistants
像我有很多助理
We often say that our symbiosis is a strawberry family
我們常常說我們協生是草莓族
I don't even admit it
我都不承認
Then his hard work
然後他那個努力的狀態
Then
然後
Then job status
然後任業的狀態
sometimes surpass us
有時候都超過我們
Never heard of them buying business
從來沒有聽過他們在買業
So don't say that we kids are strawberries
所以不要說我們小孩子是草莓族
I have found many assistants
我經過找了好多助理
I feel after passing
我經過之後覺得
Our next generation is actually very promising
我們下一代其實是很有可為的
It's just that we have to give him a good direction
只是我們要給他一個好的方向
good direction to do
好的方向來做
OK
好不好
Excuse me
不好意思
take the opportunity
趁機
flower old man
花老頭一下
OK, do you have any other questions?
OK 各位還有沒有其他問題
please
來請
Vice-Chancellor
副校長
Excuse me
不好意思
i have a test question
我有問一個試量問題
Will the quiz questions be asked publicly again?
試量問題要再公開問嗎
no
不是
I said it's about me personally
我說關係我個人的
more benefits
利益比較多一點
I am the one who ate for 38 years
我是那個38年吃的人
So I had an earlier review of the store
所以我早先對那個店
so I
我就
I'm disgusted, I don't want to study
很反感的 不想學習啊
Because our time was
因為我們那個時代是
Erection skill
勃血強技
From middle school to high school and then Wuzhuan University
從初中高中 然後武專大學這樣
grind out
磨出來
Then I always feel that the children now
那我一直覺得現在的小孩子
From the very beginning, I objected to my children learning that computer
我開始我就反對我家小孩子學習那個電腦
He becomes knowledge easy to get
他變成知識很容易得到
easy to forget
很容易忘記啊
If you ask him, he knows everything
你問他什麼都懂 什麼都不經
I don't learn it myself but
我本身就不學掉 但是
wow recently i played that
哇 最近我玩了那個
After that smartphone, wow, that sucks
那個smartphone以後啊 哇 糟糕了
This computer is really fascinating
這個電腦真的很迷人
But now the power is not good
但是現在勢力也不好
I can't write it from scratch
又不能從頭寫啊
that's why i want to say
所以我才想說
directly from this tablet
直接從這個平板電腦
Will there be a camp after the intervention?
介入以後有營端嘛
we don't need
我們就不需要
You don't have to work so hard to create a
不需要自己那麼辛苦去建立一個
your database
你的資料庫啊
So is this okay?
所以這樣子行不行啊
I think from a learning point of view this is
我想以學習的角度這個是
Good practice, because there will be no standard in the future
好好做法 因為以後也沒有標準的
software
軟體的
There's no standard software either, anyway.
也沒有標準軟體 那反正
and now the interface is very simple
而且現在使用介面都很簡單
Yeah
對 對 對
But get used to the environment
但是要習慣這個環境
After you get used to the environment and establish
你習慣環境建立起來之後
For example, you are used to communicating with others on the Internet.
譬如說你習慣跟人家在網路上溝通啊
Because some of them I haven’t faced face to face, why should I communicate with you?
因為有的我沒有面對面我幹嘛跟你溝通
it's a matter of habit
那是習慣的問題
adaptation problem
適應的問題
I think after you get used to it
我覺得你習慣適應好的之後
In fact, this can be learned at any time
其實這個隨時學習都可以
I began to think that there might be many bad things about computers
我開始覺得電腦可能會有很多不好的地方
recently feel
最近覺得
I wear it together in the morning
我早上一起穿我就
See which PPC can choose that
看那個PPC可以選擇那個
important topic
重要的題目看一看
This solves it
這樣就解決了
No wonder there is something wrong with the body
難怪那個有身體上有什麼問題
Immediately fell for Google to find
馬上上當Google去找
wow still very convenient
哇還是很方便
Much faster than finding a doctor
比找醫生快很多啊
and believe
又很相信
do you believe it
你相不相信
I have a lot of questions about the Normal University in
很多師大的問題我都是在
know on the internet
網路上面知道
So I know what's wrong with many of our students
所以我們很多學生出什麼問題我都知道
Because it is easy for me to find the information inside
因為我很容易找裡面的資料
Now what I want to write is that the first private school is not good
那現在我要寫的話就是第一個私立也不好
then many
然後很多
you that you use again
你那個你又用
The tablet will zoom in and out
平板電腦都會放大縮小
Yes, that's what I said, just intervene directly from this
對那是我說說就直接從這樣介入
don't intervene
不用再介入
ok ok ok
可以了可以了
Because in fact, our previous education was more of a crow style.
因為其實我們以前的教育是比較屬於天鴉式的啦
For example, you might be interested in literature
那天鴉式譬如說你可能對文學有興趣
So your literature will remember
所以你文學都會記得
But I can ask you how much physical chemistry do you remember?
可是我可以問你說那你物理化學到底記得多少
So sometimes the cultivation of learning ability is still very important.
所以有時候學習能力的培養還是很重要
Then you will naturally memorize the part you are interested in
那你有興趣的部分你就自然會去記
now we are not
現在我們不是啦
Now we all have to write
現在我們所有通通要寫
After finishing high school, this is a common problem
考完高中這個通通的問題
Like my personal history and geography is okay
像我個人的歷史地理還可以
forget that chemistry
那個化學忘在這
none of them are there
一個都不在
yes
沒錯
Thanks
謝謝
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他問題
please
請
I would like to ask about the positioning of future teachers
我想請教一下未來教師定位的問題
Because recently, for example, I was looking at the formula
因為最近譬如說在看公式那個
The justice of the micro-sender
micro-sender的那個正義
Harvard OpenCourseWare
就是哈佛的開放課程
We also know that MIT actually had these things a few years ago
我們也知道說MIT其實早幾年就有這些東西
In China, it is like Mr. Lu, a medicine man from the East China Sea
那國內的話像東海藥人鹿老師
A lot of the process of class is PO up
很多上課的過程都PO上 往上
And as long as the students of that relevant course go up to watch
而且只要是那一個相關學程的學生上去看
Maybe the teachers in their school have been compared
也許他們學校的老師都被比下去了
If future teachers develop like this technology
那未來的老師如果像這種科技的發展
A lot of distance learning has turned into saying that you can actually learn more than online
很多的遠端學習變成說其實在網路上就可以學到比
Better than school, the positioning of future teachers
比學校更好 那未來的老師的定位
In which direction should it develop
應該往哪個方向來發展
I mentioned that just now, actually
那個我剛才有提過其實
Transfer of knowledge through the Internet
知識面的傳遞透過網路
If you are really like the teacher you said
如果你真的就如同你講的那個老師
He is very proud of all aspects
他很為驕傲各方面
Then maybe you can watch it at home
那也許你在家裡看就好了
then no problem
那就沒有問題
That's not the problem now
那現在問題不是這個
Questions have many non-knowledgeable parts
問題有很多是非知識面的部分
The human learning of the non-knowledge part is different
那非知識面的部分的人力的學習是不一樣的
It is very difficult to express through textbooks
是很多透過教材是很難去表達的
That's why I said that teachers in the future have to transform
所以我說未來老師要去轉型
I said that after my student opened an underground website
我說我那個學生開了地下網站之後
I'm starting to transform
我就開始要轉型了
Because I know I can't teach my students anymore
因為我知道我不可能再教我的學生
in computer skills section
在電腦技能的部分
Section in Computer Science
在電腦科學的部分
What I want to teach is inquiry ability
我要教的就是探究能力
how to teach them how to form questions
怎麼教他們如何形成問題
how to solve the problem
如何去解決問題
How to use his creativity
那如何去發揮他的創意
will be different
做法就會不一樣
So don't be afraid that humans will disappear
所以不用怕人類會消失
human beings must have value
人類一定有存在的價值
My computer only expects a small part of us
我電腦只是期待我們一小部分而已
a small part
一小部分
So we're still valuable
所以我們還是很有價值
so don't worry too much about this
所以不用太擔心這個
It's not the disappearance of humans, it's the disappearance of teachers
不是人類的消失是教師的消失
no
不是
Not a Teacher Transformation
不是教師的轉型
The teacher is going to transfer
老師要去轉
Even your teacher should start to know slowly
就你老師也開始要慢慢知道說
Knowledge conveys such a
知識傳遞了這樣的一種
A role will slowly decrease
一種角色會慢慢降低
then you may have to change your other character
那你可能要改變你另外一個角色
So why are there so many institutes now
所以為什麼現在有很多研究所
It doesn't matter if he doesn't go to class at all.
他根本不上課也沒有關係啊
I don't care even if you have fewer co-marriages
我就即使你的協婚少都沒關係
no required courses
不要有必修課程
You're going to read this book because you're doing research.
因為你要做研究你本來就要去讀這個書啊
right
對不對
Why must the teacher teach you
為什麼一定要老師教你
Then the teacher will act differently
那老師的做法就會不一樣
different so there will be an adjustment
不一樣 所以會有一個調整
There will be an adjustment, you are a primary school student
會有一個調整 你又小學生
Primary school students are definitely not just passing on knowledge
小學生絕對不會只有知識的傳遞而已
Universities are more knowledge transfer
大學還是知識傳遞比較多
The development of training habits in all aspects of elementary school
那小學各方面的培訓習慣的養成各方面
In the past, we put too much emphasis on knowledge
那以前我們是太強調知識面
while ignoring other aspects
而忽略掉其他的面向
After that, other aspects may arise
那以後可能其他面向要起來
Then this teacher is going to change
那這個老師要去改變
My teacher is going to change
我老師要去改變
Do you have any other questions?
各位還沒有其他的問題
Very close
非常時間差不多
we are usually two
我們通常是兩個
Anyone else want to ask, kid, do you want to ask?
還有人要問嗎 小朋友你要問嗎
this can't stop
這個欲罷不能
Then we listened to this speech by Principal Zhang
那麼我們聽了張校長的這個演講
For this infinite world of digital learning
對這個數位學習的這個無限寬廣的天地
have an understanding
有一個了解
I'm with him to host this digital point chief
我跟他在一起主持這個數位點長
Meeting with Digital Learning National Project
跟數位學習國家型計畫的會議
For the first time after so many times, I have settled on his comprehensive view.
這麼多次 我第一次定了他全面的這個看法
I am Principal Zhang
我張校長
The Dean also reminds us
教長也提醒我們
There are a lot of side effects
這裡面有很多後遺症
And that's only a small part of it
而且這只是其中一小部分而已
So there are many places in this
所以這個裡面還有很多的地方
still worth exploring
還值得我們探索
his lecturer i think of a book
他的演講師我想起一本書
author of this book
這個書的作者
was a physical chemist in the first half of the second century
是一位二世紀上半夜的一個物理化學家
physical chemist
物理化學家
But he later studied physical chemistry
可是他後來研究物理化學
The original chapter is the last
原章都最後
he turned to philosophy
他轉向哲學了
and become a famous philosopher
而成為很有名的哲學家
His son won the Nobel Prize with Dean Li
他的兒子跟李院長一起得了諾貝爾獎
his name is prangli
他叫做普蘭里
He is a Hungarian nobleman
他是個匈牙利的貴族
He wrote a book called Personal Knowledge
他寫一本書叫Personal Knowledge
personal knowledge
個人知識
this is a classic
這是一本經典
I think there may be many people who know
我想再說可能也有很多人知道
Personal Knowledge
Personal Knowledge
This book tells us
這一本書就告訴我們
There are two kinds of knowledge we learn
我們學的知識有兩種
One is to concentrate knowledge
有一種是集中知識
There is knowledge of resources
有一種是資源的知識
Subsidial Awareness
Subsidial Awareness
is the knowledge of nearby resources
就是旁邊資源的知識
he may be a hint
他可能是一種暗示
He may be a person and an atmosphere
他可能是一個個人一個氣氛
he may be a situation
他可能是一個情境
he may be a fixer
他可能是一個修正跟
Wait, he may be out of admiration for this authority
等等 他可能是因為對這個權威的一個仰慕
And the computer doesn't give you that feeling
而電腦沒有給你這個感覺
He may be because of these things
他可能因為這些東西啊
will change your whole study of this
就會改變了你整個學習的這個
So the computer may only
所以電腦可能只能
Digital learning can be very effective
數位學習可以非常有效的
The knowledge-focused part that helps us complete
幫我們完成的集中知識的部分
resource-conscious part
他資源意識的部分
resource aware part
資源意識的部分
And there is no way to replace the part of the uncle teacher.
還有大爺老師這個部分是沒辦法取代的
the planney book
這個普蘭尼的書
i read it a long time ago
我是很久以前讀過
In fact, there is something in my impression that he said
印象中其實有一點他說
In fact, since the 19th century
他其實19世紀以來
Western labs with big breakthroughs
西方有大突破的實驗室
Most are in the tradition of his original laboratory
大部分都有他原來實驗室的傳統
Even if you give him the most complete manual for this tradition
這個傳統你即使給他最完整的手冊Manual
He can't learn it all
他也沒辦法完全學過去
he can't help
他也沒辦法
You give him this instrument
你把你給他這一台儀器
You give him all the most complete Manual
你給他全部最完整Manual給他
He still can't catch up with you up there.
他也還是沒辦法在上面趕上你
Because he has no Personal Knowledge
因為他沒有Personal Knowledge
So I think I totally agree with Principal Zhang on this
所以我想這個我完全贊成張校長的
right here
就是這裡面呢
teacher never dies
老師永遠不會死
teacher only aging
老師只有衰老
he will never disappear
他永遠不會消失
Thank you, Principal Zhang
謝謝張校長